<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Sergio Carracedo</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/</link><description>Recent content on Sergio Carracedo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Forget about installing yarn, pnpm, etc. Using Corepack</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/corepack/</link><pubDate>Sun, 26 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/corepack/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you face to manage a node.js / javascript project you should set a replicable environment, engine (node) version, package manager, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To manage the node version, you can use &lt;a href="https://github.com/nvm-sh/nvm">nvm&lt;/a> which manages the node version in your system (global and per project). You can also use a &lt;code>.nvmrc&lt;/code> file to specify the node version you need for that project and use a (shell integration)[https://github.com/nvm-sh/nvm?tab=readme-ov-file#deeper-shell-integration] to automatically switch to the correct version when you enter the project directory.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Input-field concept to improve reusability and consistency in your form-related UI components</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/input-field/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/input-field/</guid><description>&lt;p>Reusability and consistency are two concepts I am &amp;ldquo;obsessed&amp;rdquo; with. Maybe it&amp;rsquo;s because I know the effort and pain of maintaining a UI component library without those concepts in mind. It&amp;rsquo;s also about the developer experience, and the less time you spend on repetitive tasks, the more time you have to focus on the real problems and deliver value to your users. From the user&amp;rsquo;s point of view, consistency is a key factor in the usability of an application.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2024 in a Nutshell</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2024-in-a-nutshell/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2024-in-a-nutshell/</guid><description>&lt;p>2024 is over and it is time to look back and remember the milestones and achievements of the year.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="professional">Professional&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This was a year of change, I joined &lt;a href="https://newrelic.com">New Relic&lt;/a> in June as a Senior Software engineer in the UI tooling team. The challenge is big for me as the goals of the team I joined are very different from the ones in my previous roles: we are focused on providing tools to the frontend teams to improve the developer experience and ensure the quality of the frontend applications. All my previous roles were focused on the development (backend and frontend) of the product itself, but this position is not focused on the product as before. This was a big change for me and I faced many challenges, but pleased with the results and the team, a team full of talented people, great management, and something very important people who like to help and who are easy to work with.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My favourite music covers</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/music-covers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/music-covers/</guid><description>&lt;p>A cover version is a new performance or recording by someone other than the original artist typically with another production style or genre.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As is Xmas time, this is a cover of &amp;ldquo;Carol of the Bells&amp;rdquo; with metal style:&lt;/p>



&lt;iframe src="https://open.spotify.com/embed/track/2UxVAx0Ydcn4xs9FIRBczz"
width="100%"
height="152"
frameborder="0"
allowtransparency="true"
allow="encrypted-media">&lt;/iframe>


&lt;p>Long time ago, in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Napster">Napster&lt;/a> epoch, I discovered the covers, specifically punk covers of pop songs. It was a revelation for me, and I started to search for more and more covers. With the time I discovered that there are a lot of covers, not only punk covers, but also metal, rock, and other genres covers of pop songs, and also covers of other songs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Math.max (and min) 'Maximum call stack size exceeded' with large datasets and how to reimplement it to make it much faster</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/math-max-problem-fast-max/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/math-max-problem-fast-max/</guid><description>&lt;p>Even though Javascript was not created with the management of large datasets in mind, manipulating them nowadays is very common.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Data aggregation is also a common functionality, calculate the max value in an array, is a simple task, the language provides the &lt;code>Math.max&lt;/code> method to do it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But, try to do this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-ts" data-lang="ts">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">const&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">data&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span> Array.&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">from&lt;/span>({ &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">length&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">1_000_000&lt;/span> }, () &lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&amp;gt;&lt;/span> Math.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">random&lt;/span>() &lt;span style="color:#f92672">*&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">1000&lt;/span>)
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">console&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">log&lt;/span>(Math.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">max&lt;/span>(...&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">data&lt;/span>))
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>The code is simple: it generates and array with 1.000.000 random items and then tries to get the max value of the array and as the &lt;code>Math.max&lt;/code> &lt;strong>doesn&amp;rsquo;t accept an array as param, we need to spread the array to pass the values as function&amp;rsquo;s arguments&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Even more features. Lessons I Learned Creating a Table Component (4/4)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iv/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iv/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This post is part of a post series: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/">First part&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-ii/">Second part&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iii/">Third part&lt;/a>) and an extra related post: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/query-builder-filter-data/">Writing a query builder to filter data&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>As I mentioned in the previous chapters of this series, I prefer to provide the maximum number of features in the table. There are several reasons behind this decision, those are the more relevant ones:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Homogeneity&lt;/strong>: Same solution to the same problem in different places. If you don&amp;rsquo;t provide a solution for the common or repeated needs, you are taking the risk of having different solutions for the same problem. That is very common in large applications where the teams work on different parts of the application, and they can provide different solutions and different user experiences for similar use cases, this causes duplication of work and a bad user experience.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Maintainability&lt;/strong>: In general it&amp;rsquo;s easy to maintain the code, if you solve a bug it will be solved in all the places the table&amp;rsquo;s feature is used, or if a feature changes it will change in all the places, this is very related to the previous point. For example if we decide to use a recycle view to render the table rows for a better performance, we only need to do it once, and all the implementation will benefit from that.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>Implementation simplicity&lt;/strong>: Using a table with a lot of use cases and features (mostly based on configurations or props) makes it very simple to implement the table even for any developer, even if is a new-joiner or junior.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>The trade-offs of this are:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Column related features: Lessons I Learned Creating a Table Component (3/4)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iii/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This post is part of a post series: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/">First part&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-ii/">Second part&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iv/">Fourth part&lt;/a> and an extra related post: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/query-builder-filter-data/">Writing a query builder to filter data&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I want to use this last post in the series to discuss col-related features, such as col sorting, hidden cols, excluded cols, fixed cols, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="user-defined-cols-vs-internal-cols">User-defined cols vs internal cols&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s important to know that one thing is the cols defined by the user, those are data cols and are defined via the cols definition property, and another thing is the cols in general, which include the user cols, but also cols are defined by other props or features of the table (internal cols), for example the col that renders the checkboxes in the case of a selectable table, the col, that shows an arrow to expand the col, the col that renders the action buttons, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Query builder to filter data in TypeScript</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/query-builder-filter-data/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/query-builder-filter-data/</guid><description>&lt;p>I wrote posts (&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/">1&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-ii/">2&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iii/">3&lt;/a> and , &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iv/">4&lt;/a>) about my learnings creating table components, and this post can be the third part as I made a query builder for that component, but it can be used in other uses cases.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A query builder provides a convenient and (usually) simple interface for creating and executing queries (filtering) on a data set.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In TypeScript (or any other language) if you want to filter an array of objects like:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Table pagination, sorting, filtering and row selection. Lessons I learned creating a table component (2/4)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-ii/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-ii/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This post is part of a post series: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/">First part&lt;/a>), &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iii/">Third part&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iv/">Fourth part&lt;/a>, and an extra related post: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/query-builder-filter-data/">Writing a query builder to filter data&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In the &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/">first chapter&lt;/a> I talked about the data and cols definition. How to manipulate the data, transform it, and format it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This second chapter will focus on the pagination, sorting, and filtering features and the row selection.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Those features can be or cannot be the responsibility of the table, maybe you can delegate them in your code, and in some true way, but I like to provide a homogeneous and complete developer experience minimizing the repetitive tasks and putting them all together where they are needed.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Lessons I learned creating a table component (1/4)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/</link><pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-i/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This post is part of a post series: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-ii/">Second part&lt;/a>), &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iii/">Third part&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-a-table-component-iv/">Fourth part&lt;/a>, and an extra related post: &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/query-builder-filter-data/">Writing a query builder to filter data&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>I love creating UI components because they are the fundamental bricks supporting a UI application. When the components are good enough, both User and Developer experience increases, making applications consistent, easy to implement, and easy to scale.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If the UI application shows data in lists, sooner or later, you will need a table. Tables are UI components that can become very complex depending on their features. The goal of this blog post is not to tell you how to program features but to help you understand some typical needs and features tables should implement to give you useful ideas for your custom UI table component&amp;rsquo;s implementation.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Branded types in TypeScript</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/branded-types/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/branded-types/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you model entities with typescript, it is very common to get an interface like&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-ts" data-lang="ts">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">interface&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">User&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">id&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">username&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">string&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">interface&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Order&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">id&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">userId&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">title&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">string&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">year&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">month&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">day&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">amount&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> { &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">currency&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;EUR&amp;#39;&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">|&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;USD&amp;#39;&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">value&lt;/span>: &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">number&lt;/span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;h2 id="the-problem">The problem&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The properties&amp;rsquo; types have no semantic meaning. In terms of types &lt;code>User.id&lt;/code>, &lt;code>Order.id&lt;/code>, &lt;code>Order.year&lt;/code>, etc. are the same: a &lt;code>number&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Following the previous example we can have a set of functions that do actions over the entities, for example:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Are you using semicolons in JS/TS? Maybe is time to remove them</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/no-more-js-semicolons/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/no-more-js-semicolons/</guid><description>&lt;p>I have been using &lt;a href="https://standardjs.com/">standardjs&lt;/a> (and &lt;a href="https://github.com/standard/ts-standard">standardts&lt;/a>) for 5 years as &lt;em>lint&lt;/em> ruleset in my projects, and I am very happy with that. I tried before &lt;a href="https://github.com/google/eslint-config-google">Google config lint&lt;/a> and &lt;a href="https://github.com/airbnb/javascript">eslint-config-airbnb
&lt;/a> and one of the main differences I found between those rulesets is relative to semicolons; Google and Airbnb require the use of semicolons at the of the lines, but &lt;em>standardjs&lt;/em> don&amp;rsquo;t.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I worked a long time ago with PHP that requires them, but I adapted very fast to not use them in JavaScript and Go. Now I&amp;rsquo;m working on a project with a ruleset that includes the semicolons rule, and I found it a little bit uncomfortable in some situations&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Detecting circular dependencies in Javascript projects</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/circular-dependencies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/circular-dependencies/</guid><description>&lt;p>Circular imports (or circular dependencies, or cycle dependencies, but not the same as circular references) are easy to have in your code base, and more when the code grows. It can impact in the bundle generation or cause issues (for example in HMR) and you should avoid them because they are a symptom of an incorrect architecture or code organization and is a big code smell.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="what-are-circular-dependencies">What are circular dependencies&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Circular dependencies occur when a package (A) depends on another package (B) and B also depends on A. Circular dependencies can be more complex: A depends on B, B on C, C on D and D on A&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Axios interceptors to validate allowed headers</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/axios-interceptors-validate-headers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/axios-interceptors-validate-headers/</guid><description>&lt;p>Today I want to share a small tip working with CORS and Axios.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s very typical in the backend to only allow certain headers, even more so when it defines the CORS-related &lt;code>Access-Control-Request-Headers&lt;/code> header used in response to a preflight request. In those cases, if the frontend
make a request with an &lt;em>unexpected&lt;/em> header the request will be rejected.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This kind of issue mostly happens in the production environments because the browser ignores CORS headers when it
fetches data from &lt;code>localhost&lt;/code>. That is a problem as nobody will probably detect an issue sending unexpected headers
before deploying the code to production.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Monsgeek M5 custom keyboard review</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/monsgeek-m5-custom-keybord-review/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/monsgeek-m5-custom-keybord-review/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 years ago I bought my &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/25/Impresiones-tras-un-mes-de-uso-de-un-teclado-mecanico/">first mechanical keyboard&lt;/a>, a cheap and simply one, the Krom Kernel, a 100% size keyboard with Outemu Red switches with spanish layout. During this time I change the space bar keycap twice because the plastic was not very good and the part that connects with the switch was not very reliable and it broke causing a bad experience pressing it. But was something I could fix, replacing all the keycaps with a better quality ones.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A real-world "on a meeting" light sign</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/a-real-world-on-a-meeting-light-sign/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/a-real-world-on-a-meeting-light-sign/</guid><description>&lt;p>Me and my wife work remotely and we do it in the same room, but there is a problem: the meetings, and
obviously, working remotely we have, let&amp;rsquo;s say, more than we would like, and is not always easy to know when the other
is in a meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to find a solution to make it visible when someone is in a meeting simply, only with a sight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The solution: Put a light sign on the working room&amp;rsquo;s wall and turn it on when I am in a meet and off when I am not,
simple. :)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A real case: why hexagonal architecture, decoupling, and Dependency injection can be very useful in the frontend</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/hexagonal-architecture-frontend/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 May 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/hexagonal-architecture-frontend/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hexagonal architecture is a software design pattern based on the separation of responsibilities. The goal is to decouple the business logic (domain) and the application from other external interfaces.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Simplifying in hexagonal architecture we communicate the core of the app (domain + application) with the external elements using ports and adapters. A &lt;strong>port&lt;/strong> lives in the core, it is the interface any external code must use to interact with the core (or the core with the external code), the &lt;strong>adapter&lt;/strong> is the external piece of code that follows the port interface and execute the tasks, get the data, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>UI components library (Chapter II): Components anatomy and interfaces</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/ui-components-library-ii-anatomy-interfaces/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/ui-components-library-ii-anatomy-interfaces/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This is the second post of a series about why and how to create a UI components library. I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the code examples in Vue.js, but the concepts are valid for any other framework like React, Angular, LitElements, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/ui-components-library-i-why-and-to-create-one/">Chapter I: Introduction&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Before creating a components library, it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand the anatomy of a component, its interfaces, and how to create a good &amp;ldquo;API&amp;rdquo; for the components.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typescript enums: Replacing them with const and union types</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-enums-ii/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-enums-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last year &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-enums/">I wrote a post about the typescript enums&lt;/a>: how to use them, some of the disadvantages, how to mitigate them, and how to replace the enums with const enums and read-only maps.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In that post, I showed how to replace the enums with const enums and read-only maps, and I also mentioned the union types as an alternative to the enums.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this post, I want to go deeper into the union types as a replacement for the enums in some cases.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>UI components library (Chapter I): Why and to create one? Characteristics of a good UI library</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/ui-components-library-i-why-and-to-create-one/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/ui-components-library-i-why-and-to-create-one/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This is the first post of a series about why and how to create a UI components library. I&amp;rsquo;m going to focus on the code examples in Vue.js, but the concepts are valid for any other framework like React, Angular, LitElements, etc.
In this first post I&amp;rsquo;m going to talk about the component of why you should (or should not) create a UI components library, but first let&amp;rsquo;s define what is a UI components library.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2023 in a Nutshell</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2023-in-a-nutshell/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2023-in-a-nutshell/</guid><description>&lt;p>2023 is over and I did in the last years is time to summarize it. For me, it&amp;rsquo;s always an interesting exercise as I&amp;rsquo;m able to remember the challenges, achievements, and fails in the year and put things in context&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="professional">Professional&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In December 2022 I joined a new company, Nextail, and after a year I think I can review the journey.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I joined this company as Principal Frontend Engineer, my responsibility and duty was (and is) to identify the improvements needed in the frontend architecture and team organization to improve the delivery and keep growing the app.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>SPA (Vue / React / Angular) app loader</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/spa-vue-react-angular-app-loader/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Dec 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/spa-vue-react-angular-app-loader/</guid><description>&lt;p>As big a SPA is, more resources (javascript, css, images, etc.) need to load before starting to work (render/show the application in the user&amp;rsquo;s browser)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This, the time between the page starts to load and the user can interact with, is the TTI, &lt;a href="https://web.dev/articles/tti?hl=en">Time to Interactive&lt;/a>. This is an important metric for your application. &lt;strong>As higher is the value lower is the user experience&lt;/strong> using the application.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>TTI is a metric for any application, not only for SPAs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The advantage of using cache to decouple the frontend code</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/using-cache-to-decouple-frontend-code/</link><pubDate>Mon, 20 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/using-cache-to-decouple-frontend-code/</guid><description>&lt;p>We can agree decoupling is a good practice that simplifies the code and the maintainability of the project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A common way of decoupling the code is to divide the responsibilities into different layers, a very common division is:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>view layer&lt;/strong>: in charge of render HTML and interacting with the user&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>domain layer&lt;/strong>: in charge of the business logic&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;strong>infra layer&lt;/strong>: in charge of getting the data from the backend and returning it to the domain layer(here is very common to use the repository pattern, which is just a contract to get the data. The contract is unique but you can have multiple implementations, for example, one for a REST API and another for a GraphQL API, you should be able to change the implementation without changing other pieces in the code)&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s see a couple of examples use cases where it is very typical to put the performance over the decoupling. (Spoiler: we can have both)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typescript tips for legacy projects: Type only you need</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-tips/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-tips/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you introduce Typescript in a legacy project, or you are using a library that doesn&amp;rsquo;t provide types, you might be tempted to use &lt;code>any&lt;/code> for the types you will need. But this is not a good idea, because you are losing all the benefits of Typescript. &lt;strong>&lt;code>any&lt;/code> it&amp;rsquo;s something you must remove from code, and from your mind&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="type-a-shape-progressively">Type a shape progressively&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s very common to have an object with a lot of properties, and trying to type completely the shape (that is the final goal) of an object you don&amp;rsquo;t completely understand can be an overwhelming task.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Hasta luego pulpoCon</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/hasta-luego-pulpocon/</link><pubDate>Sun, 10 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/hasta-luego-pulpocon/</guid><description>&lt;p>Acaba de terminar la tercera edición de la #pulpoCon, y no será la última, pero si la última en la que yo participe como organizador.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Han sido 3 ediciones intensas en las que la conferencia ha crecido en cuanto a asistentes, patrocinadores, ponentes, etc. Y esto no es gratis, requiere un esfuerzo y dedicación que no puedo mantener. Siempre he pensado que lo que haces lo haces bien o no lo haces.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Find a item in lists in js: Performance of Set vs Array</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/js-lists-performance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Sep 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/js-lists-performance/</guid><description>&lt;p>In our apps, it&amp;rsquo;s very common to store data in lists, for example, a list of users, a list of posts, a list of selected ids, etc, and also it&amp;rsquo;s very common too need to check if a value is in the list or not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In most cases, we use simple arrays to store the data, and we use the &lt;code>includes&lt;/code> method to check if a value is in the array or not. This works and if your list is not too big, or you only need to find one element once you will not notice any performance issue, imagine the following case:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>elgato Stream Deck on Linux</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/stream-deck-linux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/stream-deck-linux/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last Christmas I got a &lt;a href="https://www.elgato.com/en/gaming/stream-deck">Elgato Stream Deck&lt;/a> as a present. My very beginning thoughts were: &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t need this, I don&amp;rsquo;t know a real use case for that&amp;rdquo;. But I decided to keep it and try to use it for something.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-a-_stream-deck_">What is a &lt;em>Stream Deck&lt;/em>?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>Stream Deck&lt;/em> is a device with 15 buttons (in my case), each button has a small screen that can show an icon or a text. The device is connected to your computer via USB and it has software that allows you to configure each button and the action to do when you press it. I think it&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;stream&amp;rdquo; because one of the typical use cases is to change the &lt;a href="https://obsproject.com/">OBS&lt;/a> scenes when you are streaming, but in general terms, you can control anything you want. You can think on it as a macro keyboard with customizable buttons, both action and key visualization.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Generative AI Models: Boosting Merchandising Analytics User Experience</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/generative-ai-models-boosting-merchandising-analytics-user-experience/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Jun 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/generative-ai-models-boosting-merchandising-analytics-user-experience/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This article was published originally in &lt;a href="https://dzone.com/articles/chatgpt-boosting-merchandising-user-experience">DZone&lt;/a>.
I wrote it in collaboration with &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mgarlorenzo/">Miguel García&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>In this article, we will explain how using the new Generative AI Models (&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model">LLM&lt;/a>) can improve the experience of business users on our &lt;a href="https://dzone.com/articles/business-analytics-tools-amp-use-cases">analytical platform&lt;/a>. Let&amp;rsquo;s say we provide our retail merchandising managers with a web application or a mobile application where they can analyze sales and stock behavior in real-time using natural language.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>These applications usually have a series of restrictions that mainly show a generic type of analysis, which users can filter or segment based on some filters and provide information such as:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Front-End: Cache Strategies You Should Know</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/front-end-cache-strategies-you-should-know/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/front-end-cache-strategies-you-should-know/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>This article was published originally in &lt;a href="https://dzone.com/articles/front-end-cache-strategies-you-should-know">DZone&lt;/a>.
I wrote it with &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/in/mgarlorenzo/">Miguel García&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://dzone.com/articles/introducing-amp-assimilating-caching-quick-read-fo">Caches&lt;/a> are very useful software components that all engineers must know. It is a transversal component that applies to all the tech areas and architecture layers such as operating systems, data platforms, backend, frontend, and other components. In this article, we are going to describe what is a cache and explain specific use cases focusing on the frontend and &lt;a href="https://dzone.com/articles/web-caching-client-side">client side&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Withdraw your library because there is another one better: It's something nice!</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/withdraw-your-library-there-is-another-better/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/withdraw-your-library-there-is-another-better/</guid><description>&lt;p>In 2019 (almost 4 years ago) I wrote an article about how to handle a &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/05/tu-propio-v-model-en-un-componente-vue/">custom v-model in Vue 2&lt;/a> (Spanish), in that article I explained how to create a custom v-model in Vue 2, the good practices synchronizing the prop and the internal status and how to avoid the warning message &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Avoid mutating a prop directly since the value will be overwritten whenever the parent component re-renders. Instead, use a data or computed property based on the prop’s value.&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CSS variables scoping to create and theme flexible ui components</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/css-variables-scoping/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/css-variables-scoping/</guid><description>&lt;p>The real name of the &lt;em>CSS variables&lt;/em> is &lt;strong>CSS Custom Properties&lt;/strong> is a draft standard (yes when I wrote these lines is on &lt;a href="https://www.w3.org/standards/history/css-variables-1">Candidate Recommendation Snapshot&lt;/a>), but is widely supported by modern browsers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;figure class="image-caption">
 &lt;img
 src="https://sergiocarracedo.es/css-variables-scoping/caniuse_hu_e2d736fd24ed63ba.jpg"
 alt="caniuse css variables"
 title=""
 width="1100"
 height="478" srcset="https://sergiocarracedo.es/css-variables-scoping/caniuse_hu_aac3a0c557f0bc09.webp 458w, https://sergiocarracedo.es/css-variables-scoping/caniuse_hu_850d585c2a31b11d.webp 768w, https://sergiocarracedo.es/css-variables-scoping/caniuse_hu_b846cd0a9c4778e8.webp 1377w" sizes="(max-width: 458px) 100vw, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, 1377px"/>
 &lt;figcaption>&lt;/figcaption>
 &lt;/figure>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>CSS variables allow us, like another kind of variable in another programming language to store a value we can reuse across our document.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typescript enums, const enums and readonly maps</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-enums/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Jan 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-enums/</guid><description>&lt;h1 id="enum-basics">Enum basics&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Enums&lt;/em> is one of the nice things Typescript bring to the Javascript development&amp;rsquo;s environment. &lt;em>Enums&lt;/em> allows you to define a set of named values (constants), generally with a semantic meaning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>One of the advantages over the regular constants is the grouping, making easy to know the different values you can use in certain place (and limiting the possible values to use)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In Typescript an enum has this shape:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2022 in a Nutshell</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2022-in-a%20nutshell/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2022-in-a%20nutshell/</guid><description>&lt;p>2022 is over, for me, it was a very intense year, with a lot of challenges, changes, laughs and memorable moments. Let&amp;rsquo;s do a small summary.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="professional">Professional&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>This was a year of change, I joined to a new company a month before the end of the year, after 2 years working in a exciting project with very smart and nice people, and after some time of resting and thinking about the future and my career.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Frontend team roles and skills, breaking the borders</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/tech-roles-in-the-frontend/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/tech-roles-in-the-frontend/</guid><description>&lt;p>15-20 years ago, web application developers had the knowledge and the technical skills necessary to create an application: HTML, CSS, JS, PHP/Python/ASP, Web Server management, MySQL/Postgres (both data and service management), etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>With time the web applications became more complex with bigger requirements. New technologies, frameworks, and paradigms bounce into the development and pushed developers to specialize in some areas arising new roles from this specialization.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nowadays, the equivalent typical roles for a web application that cover the exposed tasks/skills and the typical requirements are: Designer, Frontend developer, Backend developer, Platform engineer, and, in a data-oriented company: Data engineer, Data scientist, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typescript typing challenges and type utilities</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-typing-challenges-and-type-utilities/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-typing-challenges-and-type-utilities/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recently I was looking for more knowledge about Typescript typing, how to create more advanced and better types, and I can say that it&amp;rsquo;s a big deal, there are a lot of things you can do and, you never imagined before.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During that &amp;ldquo;investigation&amp;rdquo; I found very interesting resources I want to share with you.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="type-challenge">Type Challenge&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://tsch.js.org/">https://tsch.js.org/&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s a repository that includes a lot of, very well-documented, and designed typing challenges. Each challenge provides you a definition of it in a &lt;code>README.md&lt;/code> file, a &lt;code>test-cases.ts&lt;/code> file with the tests the type you should define should pass, and finally the file &lt;code>template.ts&lt;/code> where you should do your job creating the type necessary to meet the requirements and to pass all the tests.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using charts in the frontend: Echarts with examples</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/using-charts-frontend-echarts-with-examples/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/using-charts-frontend-echarts-with-examples/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you are working in frontend and in data visualization one of the tasks you need to solve is to represent data in
different ways (charts) and there are multiple ways of resolving it:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Do it from the scratch, with js and css, svg, canvas, etc&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using a low-level library that abstracts for you things like dom manipulation, scales, etc, &lt;a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js&lt;/a> is a very good one: I wrote a &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/understanding-d3-js-introduction/">blog post about it&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Using chart libraries&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s see some pros and cons of the different approaches there is no perfect solution, depends on your needs.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Typescript type narrowing, type guards and type predicates ([var] is [type])</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-type-narrowing/</link><pubDate>Tue, 15 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/typescript-type-narrowing/</guid><description>&lt;p>One useful feature in Typescript is &lt;em>union types&lt;/em>, for example &lt;code>string | number | null&lt;/code>, it&amp;rsquo;s a way to specify an argument, return, or variable that can get values with different types.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Type Narrowing&lt;/strong> is a technique that allows Typescript compiler to &lt;strong>reduce&lt;/strong> the types of a value evaluating &lt;strong>guard clauses&lt;/strong> in compilation time.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s see a simple example, imagine we have a function to uppercase a value that can be &lt;code>number&lt;/code>, &lt;code>string&lt;/code>, or just &lt;code>null&lt;/code>, into the function we need to handle the different cases, but at the same time Typescript can understand the types and reduce value type to the correct type in each code&amp;rsquo;s branch.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Giving (Negative) Feedback From Engineers to Managers</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/negative-feedback-from-engineers-to-managers/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/negative-feedback-from-engineers-to-managers/</guid><description>&lt;p>A couple of weeks ago my friend Miguel Garcia Lorenzo releases this quite interesting post &lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/engineering-manager-continuous-feedback-miguel-garcia-lorenzo">about the continuous feedback from the engineering managers&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I agree with all the contents of the posts, but I want to add some comments or ideas from the engineer&amp;rsquo;s point of view (it&amp;rsquo;s more about the point of view of a non-manager person).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>It&amp;rsquo;s obvious not all people have the same personality, priorities, and communication skills, and the comments I will write in the next lines don&amp;rsquo;t apply to all people.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Las arquitecturas limpias como necesidad</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/arquitecturas-limpias-como-necesidad/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/arquitecturas-limpias-como-necesidad/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Este post fue escrito originalmente e incluido en la revista de la &lt;a href="https://pulpocon.es">#pulpoCon22&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Todo tiene su momento y las soluciones que valen hoy, pueden no servir para mañana.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Por eso, cuando hablamos de arquitecturas limpias, clean code, desacomparte del framework, etc. en muchos casos nos suenan a que nuestro producto va a ser mejor solo por el hecho de aplicarlas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pero no siempre es así, hay fases en la que la simplicidad del código prima sobre su “belleza”, donde la rapidez en el delivery prima sobre la abstracción, pero lo importante es que seamos conscientes antes o despues necesitaremos arquitecturas limpias para seguir creciendo y escalando.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Generics in Golang 1.18</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/generics-in-golang-1.18/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/generics-in-golang-1.18/</guid><description>&lt;p>At the moment of writing this post Go 1.18 wasn&amp;rsquo;t released (the latest version for 1.18 is the &lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/g/golang-announce/c/QHL1fTc352o/m/5sE6moURBwAJ">Release Candidate 1&lt;/a>), but we can still play using the &lt;a href="https://go.dev/play/">playground&lt;/a> (enabling the dev branch) or installing the RC&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-bash" data-lang="bash">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>go install golang.org/dl/go1.18rc1@latest
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>go1.18rc1 download
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>One of the most interesting novelties is the &lt;em>generics&lt;/em> in a similar way we have in other languages (C#, Java, Typescript, etc&amp;hellip;). Generics allow us as developers, for example, to create a function that works with different types. The classical example Go uses in its blog to explain &lt;a href="https://go.dev/blog/why-generics">why generics&lt;/a> (highly recommended), is a function that does some operation over an array, for example, reverse the array. Now we must write the same function for different types, ex: int, float, string, etc&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Running workflows in you k8s cluster: Argo Workflows</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/running-workflows-in-you-k8s-cluster-argo-workflows/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/running-workflows-in-you-k8s-cluster-argo-workflows/</guid><description>&lt;p>Simplifying it, a workflow is a list of tasks to run in some order and/or fulfilling some dependencies, for example, if we have 5 tasks to run: &lt;code>A&lt;/code>, &lt;code>B&lt;/code>, &lt;code>C&lt;/code>, &lt;code>D&lt;/code>, &lt;code>E&lt;/code>.
Task &lt;code>C&lt;/code> depends on finishing tasks &lt;code>A&lt;/code> and &lt;code>B&lt;/code>, task &lt;code>D&lt;/code> depends on finishing &lt;code>C&lt;/code> and &lt;code>E&lt;/code>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Something like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="grafo.svg"alt="Grafo" title="" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are several tools to orchestrate that, but we&amp;rsquo;ll focus on &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://argoproj.github.io/argo-workflows/">Argo Workflows&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Argo Workflows is an open-source container-native workflow engine for orchestrating parallel jobs on &lt;em>Kubernetes&lt;/em>.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Dealing with infinite pagination</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/dealing-with-infinite-pagination/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/dealing-with-infinite-pagination/</guid><description>&lt;p>In the software development context, pagination is the process of dividing a list of items (rows) into groups of the same size.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example if we have these items:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-js" data-lang="js">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">const&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">items&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span> [&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">1&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">2&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">3&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">4&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">5&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">6&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">7&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">8&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">9&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">10&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">11&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">12&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">13&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">14&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">15&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">16&lt;/span>]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>and we want to paginate in pages (groups) of 5 elements we should know the list or the total items in the list, and we can calculate the number of pages, and how to get the items on a page (I&amp;rsquo;m assuming that the page value starts in 0)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Integration tests in Golang with dockertest</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/integration-tests-in-golang-with-dockertest/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/integration-tests-in-golang-with-dockertest/</guid><description>&lt;p>Do integration testing (or system testing) usually means to have a database populated with data, services like redis, elasticsearch, etc&amp;hellip; working, In general, any infrastructure with which our software interacts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The most common way to do it is to have a replica of our production infrastructure. Actually, it&amp;rsquo;s relatively easy to achieve using containers, for example, docker containers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can set up and run a container for every service we need to replicate, we can orchestrate it with docker-compose and create some makefiles or just a simple script to prepare the infrastructure and run the integration tests.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vue Composition API: How to split and reuse code</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/vue-composition-api-how-to-split-and-reuse-code/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/vue-composition-api-how-to-split-and-reuse-code/</guid><description>&lt;p>The Vue Composition API arrived at us in Nov 2018, 2 years ago, as a &lt;a href="https://medium.com/vue-mastery/evan-you-previews-vue-js-3-0-ab063dec3547">preview&lt;/a> and become with &lt;a href="https://dev.to/danielelkington/vue-s-darkest-day-3fgh">some controversial&lt;/a>, because people believed composition API would replace the traditional Object API, but would not.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Anyway, after start to develop Vue apps using the composition API I don&amp;rsquo;t want to go back, maybe for very small components makes you write more code than with the Object API, but in most cases, you can take advantage of the composition API features.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Database migrations in Golang.</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/database-migrations-in-golang/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/database-migrations-in-golang/</guid><description>&lt;p>During the development of an app, it&amp;rsquo;s very common to do changes in the database schema, for a new feature you need to add a new table, add a new column to an existing table, alter the type of existing column or delete a column.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you work alone you could do it manually, run the queries to alter the database schemas manually.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>What happens when your team is not a one-person team? You need to share the queries to change the schema with your teammates, and they should know what changes they applied before to know if there are some new changes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Creating custom events in JS</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-custom-events-in-js/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/creating-custom-events-in-js/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you try to encapsulate features but need to interact with async events or events generated by user interaction, one of the easiest ways to achieve that is using event and event handlers (often called callbacks).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine you have a UI component to render a TO-DO list with a button to create a TO-DO item through a form. This component is self-encapsulated, you only need to put the component in your app, and the component itself renders the list, the button, the form, do the request to API, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to create a table with a fixed header</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/how-to-create-a-table-with-a-fixed-header/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/how-to-create-a-table-with-a-fixed-header/</guid><description>&lt;p>Tables in HTML are one of the older things in the standard, even before CSS we had HTML tables. In the past tables were used to markup the webpages, but the correct usage is to display tabular data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Over time the standard improves the table styling covering most of the use cases you can consider.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But, there is a use case it&amp;rsquo;s not easy to get with the table attributes or style properties, I&amp;rsquo;m talking about creating a table with a fixed/sticky header (or footer).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Soy casi un boomer y consumo Twitch: Mis streams favoritos</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/mis-streams-favoritos-de-twitch/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Aug 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/mis-streams-favoritos-de-twitch/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Disclaimer: Este es mi primer post en castellano en bastante tiempo, el motivo es el contenido del que voy a hablar
está mayoritariamente en castellano y sería un poco raro hacerlo en inglés&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Como dice el título, ya soy casi un boomer, lo que para muchos estereotipos me haría ser el típico consumidor de
televisión en mis horas de entretenimiento, pero desde unos hace 4-5 años he ido reduciendo mi consumo televisivo poco a
poco a prácticamente 0.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How to run GitHub Actions in local with Act</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/act-how-to-run-github-actions-in-local/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/act-how-to-run-github-actions-in-local/</guid><description>&lt;p>GitHub Actions is a powerful tool, you can run tests, build your app, deploy it, even &lt;a href="https://github.blog/2021-04-22-github-actions-update-helping-maintainers-combat-bad-actors/">mining bitcoins&lt;/a> &amp;#x1f614;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When you are creating an action or workflow in GitHub Actions, it is very common the needing of test it, check if all works as you need and if something is not correct, fix it, in other works as other software GitHub Actions need to be iterated.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Doing it in GitHub have disadvantages:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Simplifying the use of custom a Vue v-model</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/vue-use-model-helpers/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/vue-use-model-helpers/</guid><description>&lt;p>One year ago I wrote a post about how to manage your
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/05/tu-propio-v-model-en-un-componente-vue/">custom v-model in your component&lt;/a>
(&lt;em>Spanish&lt;/em>).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The problem still being the same, if you try to mutate the value of the property into the component you will get this error message:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Error message: Avoid mutating a prop directly since the value will be overwritten whenever the parent component re-renders. Instead, use a data or computed property based on the prop’s value.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tips using Typescript and Vue</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/tips-using-typescript-and-vue/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/tips-using-typescript-and-vue/</guid><description>&lt;p>Typescript is a great &amp;ldquo;language&amp;rdquo;, makes it possible to create more maintainable and understandable software, but requires extra effort to type the variables, the functions&amp;rsquo; arguments, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vue 2.x, and even more Vue 3 provide a great typescript integration, providing the necessary types to use your app, but not always are trivial, and you need to know the types you must use in every case.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I want to share with all of you the lessons I learned in my experience using Vue and TS, the typical questions, and the &amp;ldquo;problems&amp;rdquo; I found in the way.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Understanding d3.js - A simple line chart</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/understanding-d3-js-introduction/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/understanding-d3-js-introduction/</guid><description>&lt;p>Before starting is important to say that &lt;strong>d3.js is not a chart library is a library for making charts&lt;/strong>, if you are expecting to pass the data to the library and set 4, 5,&amp;hellip; 10 params and get the chart to render, d3.js is not your library.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://d3js.org/">d3.js&lt;/a> is more than that, is a very flexible library to manage data (data-driven documents) and create the representation of that data (not only charts). &lt;strong>d3.js&lt;/strong> provides you the different pieces to create your customized data visualizations (for example charts)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Custom SVG icon set management with Vue</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/custom-svg-icon-set-management-with-vue/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/custom-svg-icon-set-management-with-vue/</guid><description>&lt;p>Manage an icon set can seem a simple task but can be tricky.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>First, there a lot of ways to use an icon on a web page, all with pros and contras:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Let&amp;rsquo;s use this SVG image created by &lt;a href="https://freeicons.io/profile/730">Anu Rocks&lt;/a> for all examples.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>We will assume our icon set is monochrome.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://freeicons.io/common-ui-icons/battery-medium-icon-54110">&lt;img src="example.svg"alt="" title="" />&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&lt;h2 id="img-tag">&amp;lt;img&amp;gt; tag&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The simplest way of adding an icon is using the &lt;code>&amp;lt;img&amp;gt;&lt;/code> tag as the other images.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Deploying a static website in Azure Static Web Apps</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/azure-static-web-apps/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/azure-static-web-apps/</guid><description>&lt;p>Nowadays &lt;a href="https://jamstack.org/">JAMStack&lt;/a> is trendy because a lot of reasons: performance, security, decoupling, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>JAMStack consists of pre-rendering your website or application&amp;rsquo;s frontend and get the dynamic data from an API.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Your pre-rendered markup can be host in a server, but as it is static, your host only needs to serve static files, just HTML, CSS, and JS. You don&amp;rsquo;t need to run any code on the server.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>There are a lot of different options to deploy a static website, for example:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>2020 in a nutshell</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020-in-a-nutshell/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020-in-a-nutshell/</guid><description>&lt;p>2020 is almost complete, and it was a year that we will remember for a long time. I don&amp;rsquo;t want to be dramatic, but 2020 left a deep mark on all of us.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="profesional">Profesional&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>In the professional terrain, in January I started a new job as a pure frontend guy in a big company. This job gives to me a big opportunity of work with amazing people. This job forces me to speak in English most of the time, this is the reason why I started to write this blog in English. It was a challenge and still being, but I&amp;rsquo;m always very happy to be challenged. In November, I moved to a new job an awesome professional opportunity, but a great opportunity to be part of a project whose goal is to help others and to make a better and more equitable world.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Webkit (Safari) memory leak using SVG filters</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/2020/safari-svg-filters-memory-leak/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/2020/safari-svg-filters-memory-leak/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="the-context">The context&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A few weeks ago I was developing a website using &lt;a href="https://nuxtjs.org/">NuxtJs&lt;/a> (which is not important for the problem but the is the context &amp;#x1f609; ). That was a website that needs to use a few images as building blocks, the typical section separator with a shape different to a simple line, in this case, the section&amp;rsquo;s separator had 2 colors and a shadow.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to use SVG images for several reasons, for example the images had to adapt to different screen widths, and the images were simple (more complex than a line but simple, They were similar to 2 waves with 2 colors). The SVG files are very useful in these use case, because the file size is small, and you can scale them infinitely without lost definition.&lt;br>
One important thing in this issue as we&amp;rsquo;ll see later is that this image had a shadow.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Talk: Creating your own Vue UI components library: From scratch to NPM</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/2020/creating-your-own-vue-ui-components-library-from-scratch-to-npm/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/2020/creating-your-own-vue-ui-components-library-from-scratch-to-npm/</guid><description>&lt;p>Past September 29th I did a talk about how to create your own Vue UI components.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I explained some tips about how to organize the components&amp;rsquo; code, talked in deep about how to set the values in &lt;code>package.json&lt;/code> and their meaning. And how to publish on NPM and then how to use them in another project.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The talk was in Spanish, but slides are in English.&lt;/p>

 &lt;div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
 &lt;iframe allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen="allowfullscreen" loading="eager" referrerpolicy="strict-origin-when-cross-origin" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/z_K5iuSjCDo?autoplay=0&amp;amp;controls=1&amp;amp;end=0&amp;amp;loop=0&amp;amp;mute=0&amp;amp;start=0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" title="YouTube video">&lt;/iframe>
 &lt;/div>

&lt;iframe frameborder="0" marginheight="0" marginwidth="0" width="100%" height="600" type="text/html" src="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/e/2PACX-1vS9j4GjB2eZrnGI9b47FbecBunSSa_zYPJJsNu2mcJ_uux4CbisJOdG6vaFXB9rPTiPnv4N_KeXlLPl/embed?start=false&amp;amp;loop=false&amp;amp;delayms=5000">&lt;/iframe></description></item><item><title>Automate the startup of your projects with yarn create and SAOjs</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/automate-project-startup-with-yarn-create/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/automate-project-startup-with-yarn-create/</guid><description>&lt;p>Start a project in any language, framework, etc it&amp;rsquo;s not as simple as it seems. I mean, usually, the project requires a lot of configuration files, installing dependencies, set the environment, create skeleton files, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Talking about JavaScript frameworks: everyone has his own CLI tool to start a project with the required files to start to code.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For example &lt;strong>Angular&lt;/strong> has &lt;a href="https://cli.angular.io/">@angular/cli&lt;/a> and you could execute &lt;code>ng new [app-name]&lt;/code>or
&lt;strong>Vue&lt;/strong> has &lt;a href="https://cli.vuejs.org/">@vue/cli&lt;/a> and you can start a Vue project executing &lt;code>vue create [project name]&lt;/code>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How Vue's reactivity works (I): Object.defineProperty</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/how-vue-reactivity-works-i/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/how-vue-reactivity-works-i/</guid><description>&lt;p>Maybe you don&amp;rsquo;t need to know how Vue reactivity works under the hood to make Vue apps, but anyway it will be interesting and useful.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In this context &lt;strong>reactivity&lt;/strong>, means, simplifying, the capacity to detect a data change and do something after that.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In a Vue component, &lt;strong>reactivity&lt;/strong>, means that the component will be re-rendered (totally or partially) after a change in the value of a variable to show the component updated with the new value. For example in this basic component:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Is know how to search on Google a skill?</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/is-search-in-google-a-skill/</link><pubDate>Mon, 31 Aug 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/is-search-in-google-a-skill/</guid><description>&lt;p>Most of us do search on Google every day, maybe looking for a website, for news, for an address, for a cooking recipe, for information about a topic we are interested in, for technical information or anything.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>All developers I know use Google, another search engine, or search on webpages like &lt;a href="https://stackoverflow.com/">stack overflow&lt;/a> every day to find the best way to do a task.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>So is it a skill?, Should you know how to resolve a task without using Google or another knowledge source?&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>What is VuePress and why you should use it to document your project?</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/vuepress/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/vuepress/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://vuepress.vuejs.org/">VuePress&lt;/a> defines itself as a &lt;em>Vue-powered Static Site Generator&lt;/em>. In other words, is a tool to create static sites. A static site is a website where nothing runs on the server. The server only takes care of return the file (HTML file) as is stored in the server.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Is the opposite of a &lt;strong>dynamic site&lt;/strong>, like for example a PHP webpage, in that case, your browser makes a request to the server, and the server executes PHP code that, for example, get a post from a database, process it, put that post in an HTML template, etc and returns the result to the browser.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Export and import Vuex state</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/07/22/export-and-import-vuex-state/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/07/22/export-and-import-vuex-state/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you are familiarized with Vuex, you must know that Vuex is a &lt;a href="https://vuex.vuejs.org/#what-is-vuex">state management pattern library&lt;/a> for Vue applications. Vuex centralizes the application&amp;rsquo;s state and how components, and other code parts, change it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You can find a lot of articles talking about Vuex, I even wrote 2 articles 3 year ago talking about it:
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/03/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-i/" title="Vuex el redux de VueJS I">Vuex el redux de VueJS I&lt;/a>
and
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/03/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-i/" title="Vuex el redux de VueJS II">Vuex el redux de VueJS II&lt;/a> (&lt;em>Spanish&lt;/em>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sharing variables between SCSS and Typescript</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/07/17/sharing-variables-between-scss-and-typescript/</link><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/07/17/sharing-variables-between-scss-and-typescript/</guid><description>&lt;p>Sometimes you need to share variables between CSS (or SCSS) and Typescript, for example, if you have a list of colors in your SCSS file and need to check the variable names in typescript to be sure is an available color.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Imagine a Vue component have a property to set the background color:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-html" data-lang="html">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&amp;lt;&lt;span style="color:#f92672">template&lt;/span>&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &amp;lt;&lt;span style="color:#f92672">div&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">:class&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;[&amp;#39;component&amp;#39;, colorClass]&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> My component
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &amp;lt;/&lt;span style="color:#f92672">div&lt;/span>&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&amp;lt;/&lt;span style="color:#f92672">template&lt;/span>&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&amp;lt;&lt;span style="color:#f92672">script&lt;/span>&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">const&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">availableColors&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span> [&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;primary&amp;#39;&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;alert&amp;#39;&lt;/span>, &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;my-custom-color&amp;#39;&lt;/span>]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">export&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">default&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">name&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;my-component&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">props&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">color&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> String
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">computed&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">colorClass&lt;/span> () { 
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">if&lt;/span> (&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">availableColors&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">indexOf&lt;/span>(&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">this&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">color&lt;/span>) &lt;span style="color:#f92672">!==&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">-&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#ae81ff">1&lt;/span>) {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">return&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">`color-&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">${&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">this&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">color&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">}&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">`&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> } 
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">return&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">null&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> } 
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>}
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&amp;lt;/&lt;span style="color:#f92672">script&lt;/span>&amp;gt;
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>In this component, if you set the property color, and the value is an available color, adds a class for that color, for example, if the color prop is &lt;code>primary&lt;/code> adds the class &lt;code>.color-primary&lt;/code>, but if the prop&amp;rsquo;s value is &lt;code>red&lt;/code> doesn&amp;rsquo;t add any class related to color because &lt;code>red&lt;/code> is not an available color.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Why I write a blog</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/07/15/why-i-write-a-blog/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/07/15/why-i-write-a-blog/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you are here (Welcome!) you are reading my blog, this is obvious &amp;#x1f602;, and I want to share with you why I write it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Writing a blog is in some ways a hard task:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>You should find an interesting topic to write about.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Look for information related to the chosen topic.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Read a lot of references about it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Write your blog post.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Review it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Correct it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Find a beautiful and related picture for the header and home page.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>And finally publish it.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>You could also want to share on Twitter or LinkedIn.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Ok, but why do you do this &amp;ldquo;effort&amp;rdquo;? In somehow I do this thinking of myself:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Improving your Vue (and JS) coding quality and workflow</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/06/21/Improving-your-JS-workflow/</link><pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 12:47:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/06/21/Improving-your-JS-workflow/</guid><description>&lt;p>To start coding Javascript (and other languages), you almost need nothing, just a simple, text editor. That is good to start coding when you are learning the language, just code without distractions.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>But when you develop bigger projects or/and with others, some problems appears: code organization, coding style, and other. That is because all languages have at a least clean code style guide.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Things like use semi-colon or not at the end of the line, the number of spaces indenting code, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>My favorite YouTube Channels 2020</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/06/02/my-favourite-youtube-channels-2020/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/06/02/my-favourite-youtube-channels-2020/</guid><description>&lt;p>In 2018, I did a list of my
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/11/29/Mis-canales-favoritos-de-YouTube/">favourite YouTube Channels&lt;/a> (Spanish), almost 2 years pass after this post and on this time I start to watch new channels and remove or watch less other channels.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This year I classified the videos by topic (as I did last year), and I added an emoji code:&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&amp;#x2b50; Favorite channel. I usually watch most videos.
&amp;#x2757; Very interesting
&amp;#x1f525; Some videos are very interesting&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Creating a simple donut progress chart</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/05/18/Creating-a-simple-donut-chart/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 09:28:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/05/18/Creating-a-simple-donut-chart/</guid><description>&lt;p>One of more simpler charts you can create is a circular chart to represent the percent of completion of something.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="first-approximation">First approximation&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>We could create a SVG document to draw our donut. SVG allow us to represent graphical elements, for example, cicles, rectangles, polygons, etc&amp;hellip; using XML (and therefore accesing to the elements via DOM). SVG is vertorial and is perfect for responsive.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="01.svg"alt="" title="" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Figure 1 represent that kind of chart, if the value is 100% the donut is perfect, if is 50% donut is a half donut, and 0% means no donut.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Javascript unary operators: Taking advantage using them</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/05/09/js-unary-operators-and-taking-advantage/</link><pubDate>Sat, 09 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/05/09/js-unary-operators-and-taking-advantage/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="whats-an-operator">What&amp;rsquo;s an operator?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>An operator is a symbol that define the operation to do between 1 o more operands.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;figure class="image-caption">
 &lt;img
 src="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/05/09/js-unary-operators-and-taking-advantage/operators_hu_2feb7a0840e91c39.jpg"
 alt=""
 title=""
 width="1100"
 height="505" srcset="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/05/09/js-unary-operators-and-taking-advantage/operators_hu_104595e8d1c01e7f.webp 499w" sizes="499px"/>
 &lt;figcaption>&lt;/figcaption>
 &lt;/figure>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We use a lot of operators: sum (+), subtraction (-), multiply (*), division (/), logic and (&amp;amp;&amp;amp;), negation (!),&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="whats-a-unary-operator">What&amp;rsquo;s a unary operator?&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>A unary operator is an operator that only needs one operand to work.
For example&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">i&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">++&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>In this example we have an operand (&lt;code>i&lt;/code>) and an operator (&lt;code>++&lt;/code>), we don&amp;rsquo;t need more to increment the &lt;code>i&lt;/code> variable value.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Understanding Javascript's event loop: Macrotasks and microtasks</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/04/27/js-loop/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/04/27/js-loop/</guid><description>&lt;p>Despite what it may seem, Javascript execution in a browser is &lt;em>synchronous&lt;/em>. It is a similar thing as a &lt;em>multitask&lt;/em> OS running in a mono-core processor, in that case multitasking is &amp;ldquo;fake&amp;rdquo;, because the processor can only execute one instruction at a time, but the OS controls the execution and distribute the processor time between each app, making it looks like multitasking.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;em>Javascript&lt;/em> we have a similar approximation in a way to distribute the execution time. It&amp;rsquo;s not exactly the same. Lets see how it works.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Slimbook ProX 15: First Impressions</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/04/05/slimbook-prox15-first-impressions/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/04/05/slimbook-prox15-first-impressions/</guid><description>&lt;p>As you probably know, I started a new job this year, and my company provided me a laptop. They asked me which laptop I would like to use to work, most people would answer: MacBook Pro or something like that, but I don&amp;rsquo;t like Apple (sorry, those are my likes, maybe you have different ones), and I prefer Linux as my OS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My first choice was a Dell XPS 15 with 16GB of RAM, but after several delays in delivery, my company and I were tired of waiting and we decided to order another laptop.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Start using Typescript in Vue. The easy way.</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/02/27/start-using-typescript-in-vue-easy-way/</link><pubDate>Thu, 27 Feb 2020 10:58:02 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/02/27/start-using-typescript-in-vue-easy-way/</guid><description>&lt;p>If you program in &lt;em>JavaScript&lt;/em> probably somebody told you about the advantages of using &lt;em>Typescript&lt;/em> or you thought about start using it.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As you can see in this chart, more than 50% &lt;em>Javascript&lt;/em> developers are using &lt;em>Typescript&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sergiocarracedo.es/images/javascript_flavors_section_overview.png"alt="" title="" />
&lt;em>Source: &lt;a href="https://2019.stateofjs.com/javascript-flavors/">https://2019.stateofjs.com/javascript-flavors/&lt;/a>&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Start to use a new technology, new paradigm, new framework or anything could be hard and challenging, this is why is important start integrating new technologies avoiding friction with previous one. Today I&amp;rsquo;ll try to show you the easiest way to start using &lt;em>Typescript&lt;/em> in your Vue projects.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Using same avatar in different accounts and avoid confusion</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/02/26/same-avatar-in-diferent-account/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 09:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/02/26/same-avatar-in-diferent-account/</guid><description>&lt;p>Probably you have several internet services accounts, and some in the same service, for example two &lt;em>gmail&lt;/em> accounts, one for work and a personal, or
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/23/instagram-rbg/" title="multiple Instagram accounts as me">multiple Instagram accounts as me&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I like to use same picture as avatar in each account, but the problem is difficult to differentiate the account you are logged in only watching the avatar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m using a simple tip to differentiate them, add a color band at the bottom of the image, the point is to use same color for every single account or role, for example you could use black for work, and green for personal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>(Deep) Cloning objects in Javascript</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/deep-cloning-objects-in-javascript/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Feb 2020 18:28:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/deep-cloning-objects-in-javascript/</guid><description>&lt;p>Cloning objects in &lt;em>Javascript&lt;/em> (and in other languages) is a tricky task. JS doesn’t store the object value in your variable or in your constant, instead, stores a pointer to the object value (the object reference).&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Even when you pass an object to a function or method, you are passing this object by reference, not the value.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you pass (or copy) an object by reference and then change any property, the ‘source’ object’s property also changes.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vue Router lazy loading and chunking</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/29/vue-router-lazy-loading-and-chunking/</link><pubDate>Sun, 29 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/29/vue-router-lazy-loading-and-chunking/</guid><description>&lt;p>When you start to create SPA &lt;em>(Single page application)&lt;/em> you must bear in mind that SPA doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean &lt;em>Single JavaScript file&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>You normally use &lt;em>Webpack&lt;/em> to handle your app builds, by default, &lt;em>Webpack&lt;/em> create one file for all assets, &lt;em>even CSS&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The first step, maybe, is separate styles from &lt;em>app.js&lt;/em> in their own CSS files.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To do this, we&amp;rsquo;ll use the &lt;em>Webpack&lt;/em> plugin &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://webpack.js.org/plugins/mini-css-extract-plugin/">MiniCssExtractPlugin&lt;/a>&lt;/em> which we&amp;rsquo;ll configure like this:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-js" data-lang="js">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">// webpack.config.js
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">const&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">MiniCssExtractPlugin&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">require&lt;/span>(&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;mini-css-extract-plugin&amp;#39;&lt;/span>);
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">module&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">exports&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">plugins&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">new&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">MiniCssExtractPlugin&lt;/span>({
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">filename&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;[name].css&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> })
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ],
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">module&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">rules&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">test&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">/\.css$/&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">use&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">loader&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">MiniCssExtractPlugin&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">loader&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">options&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">publicPath&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;/public/path/to/&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;css-loader&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ... &lt;span style="color:#75715e">// Other loaders like sass-loader or postcss-loader
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">&lt;/span> ],
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ...
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>This forces &lt;em>Webpack&lt;/em> to extract CSS into separated files, for example &lt;code>app.css&lt;/code>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Instagram RGB Project</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/23/instagram-rbg/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/23/instagram-rbg/</guid><description>&lt;p>This is my first post in English. I joined a team whose main language is English and I need to improve it &amp;#x1f61e;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I will start writing about non-technical topics, in this case about my 3 public Instagram accounts.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="red">Red&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>About 3 years ago, in 2016, I decided to create an Instagram account only for red things pictures because I thought in the global visual effect in the account profile page. This is the effect I am talking about:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Simracing: Muy real y mucho real</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/11/simracing-mas-real-que-virtual/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/11/simracing-mas-real-que-virtual/</guid><description>&lt;p>Llevo mucho tiempo jugando a simuladores de conducción, especialmente de F1, y cuando digo mucho tiempo, es mucho tiempo, más de 20 años &amp;#x1f613;, desde el &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qATaCWHLAxw">Microprose Grand Prix&lt;/a> hasta uno de los más actuales que he jugado: &lt;a href="https://www.lfs.net/">Live for Speed&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Nótese que hablo de &lt;strong>simuladores&lt;/strong> no de juegos de coches en general. Y por simulador podemos entender que el juego trata de imitar de la formas más realista posible la experiencia de conducción y competición: Principalmente las físicas del vehículo: Amortiguaciones, Ruedas (temperaturas, desgaste, suciedad), aerodinámica, ángulos de caída, motor, inercias, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tu propio v-model en un componente Vue (The right way)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/05/tu-propio-v-model-en-un-componente-vue/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/05/tu-propio-v-model-en-un-componente-vue/</guid><description>&lt;p>Si has usado componentes de Vue (o incluso un input básico) habrás usado &lt;code>v-model&lt;/code> para enlazar un valor en el componente padre y en el componente hijo.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-js" data-lang="js">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">input&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">v&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">-&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">model&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;message&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">// o
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#75715e">&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">datepicker&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">v&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">-&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">model&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">=&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#34;date&amp;#34;&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">&amp;gt;&amp;lt;&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#960050;background-color:#1e0010">/datepicker&amp;gt;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Si en el componente padre (aquel donde incluimos &lt;em>datepicker&lt;/em>) modificamos el valor de &lt;code>date&lt;/code> automáticamente se modificará el valor dentro del componente, de igual forma si el componente modifica el valor de &lt;code>date&lt;/code> el valor se modificará en el padre. Esto lo que permite, por ejemplo, es que cuando en un campo input escribimos algo en el componente padre se pueda mostrar lo que escribimos usando &lt;code>{% raw %}{{ date }}{% endraw %}&lt;/code>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Programación funcional en PHP: Un poco de teoría y Lambdish/phunctional</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/03/programacion-funcional-en-php/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/12/03/programacion-funcional-en-php/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hace unas semanas &lt;a href="https://twitter.com/felixgomezlopez">@felixgomexlopez&lt;/a> me habló de una librería en PHP que te ofrecía un montón de funciones para manejar iterables y funciones de primera clase (u orden superior) en programación funcional, así que la he probado y (spoiler) me ha encantado.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Antes de nada veamos algunos conceptos importantes de la &lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Programaci%C3%B3n_funcional">programación funcional&lt;/a>:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="funciones-de-primera-clase-o-de-orden-superior">Funciones de primera clase o de orden superior&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Son aquellas que pueden recibir como parámetros otra función, por ejemplo la función &lt;a href="https://www.php.net/manual/es/function.array-map.php">&amp;lsquo;array_map&amp;rsquo;&lt;/a> de PHP, recibe dos argumentos, un &lt;em>callable&lt;/em> y un &lt;em>array&lt;/em>, devolviendo una matriz con el resultado de aplicar el &lt;em>callable&lt;/em> (normalmente una función) a cada elemento de la matriz original.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>PHP Reflection: Anotaciones, PHPDoc y mucho más</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/11/01/php-reflection/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/11/01/php-reflection/</guid><description>&lt;p>La &lt;a href="https://www.php.net/manual/es/intro.reflection.php">reflexíón en PHP&lt;/a> es algo que nunca he usado, y que posiblemente no usaré más allá de curiosear su funcionamiento como en este &lt;em>post&lt;/em> (como otras muchas veces es posible que me trague estas palabras &amp;#x1f604;), y creo que la mayoría de vosotros tampoco ha usado.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Esta este conjunto de clases está con nosotros desde PHP 5.0, es decir desde julio de 2004 (hace ahora más de 15 años &amp;#x1f613;) y nos proveen un sistema para hacer ingeniería inversa de clases, interfaces, métodos, propiedades, generadores, incluso extensiones del lenguaje.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Composition API: Las novedades de Vue 3 en Vue 2.x</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/10/26/composition-api-las-novedades-de-vue-3-en-vue-2-x/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/10/26/composition-api-las-novedades-de-vue-3-en-vue-2-x/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hace ahora casi un año, &lt;strong>Evan You&lt;/strong>, creador de Vue, durante la &lt;a href="https://medium.com/vue-mastery/evan-you-previews-vue-js-3-0-ab063dec3547">VueConf presentó una &lt;em>preview&lt;/em>&lt;/a> de lo que será &lt;strong>Vue 3&lt;/strong> cuyas principales lineas maestras son:&lt;/p>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>Más rápido&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Más pequeño&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Un código más mantenible&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Más amistoso con entornos nativos (Android, iOS, Desktop, etc.)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>Más fácil de usar&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;p>Una de las novedades, que nos traerá es lo que en ese momento se llamó &lt;strong>Hooks API&lt;/strong> (&lt;a href="https://vue-composition-api-rfc.netlify.com/#comparison-with-react-hooks">inspirado en React Hooks&lt;/a>), y que ha pasado a llamarse &lt;strong>Composition API&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mi entorno de trabajo: Hardware &amp; Software</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/10/06/mi-entorno-de-trabajo-hardware-software/</link><pubDate>Sun, 06 Oct 2019 20:08:40 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/10/06/mi-entorno-de-trabajo-hardware-software/</guid><description>&lt;p>Es raro que, tras algún &lt;em>meetup&lt;/em>, en las cañas de después, no se hable de el hardware y software que cada uno usa, normalmente por que alguien está pensando en cambiar un dispositivo o por que se comentan las ventajas de tal o cual IDE.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Así que me he decidido a hacer un pequeño inventario de hardware y software de mi entorno de desarrollo para no olvidarme de nada.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="hardware">Hardware&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Aunque dispongo de un portátil, normalmente desarrollo en un PC de escritorio que uso a veces tambien para jugar:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Simplificando la gestión del router de Vue</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/10/02/simplificando-la-gestion-del-router-de-vue/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 16:47:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/10/02/simplificando-la-gestion-del-router-de-vue/</guid><description>&lt;p>Cuando creamos nuestra aplicación Vue una de las cosas que debemos configurar, si nuestra app dispone de varias páginas, es el &lt;a href="https://router.vuejs.org/guide/#javascript">router&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Vue dispone de un router propio lo suficientemente bueno para que no necesites usar ningún otro y que se configura de una forma similar a esta:&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="highlight">&lt;pre tabindex="0" style="color:#f8f8f2;background-color:#272822;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;">&lt;code class="language-javascript" data-lang="javascript">&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">import&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Vue&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">from&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;vue&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">import&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Router&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">from&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;vue-router&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">import&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Login&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">from&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;../pages/Login&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">import&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Home&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">from&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;../pages/Home&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">import&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Article&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">from&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;../pages/Article&amp;#39;&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Vue&lt;/span>.&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">use&lt;/span>(&lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Router&lt;/span>)
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>&lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">new&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Router&lt;/span>({
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">routes&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> [
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">path&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;/login&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">name&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;login&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">component&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Login&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">path&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;/&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">name&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;home&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">component&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Home&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">meta&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">auth&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">true&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">path&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;/articulo/:slug&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">name&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#e6db74">&amp;#39;home&amp;#39;&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">props&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">true&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">component&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">Article&lt;/span>,
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">meta&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> {
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> &lt;span style="color:#a6e22e">auth&lt;/span>&lt;span style="color:#f92672">:&lt;/span> &lt;span style="color:#66d9ef">true&lt;/span>
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> }
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> },
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span> ]
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;span style="display:flex;">&lt;span>})
&lt;/span>&lt;/span>&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>&lt;p>Como vemos las cada ruta se define en un Objeto dentro de un Array, indicando el &lt;em>path&lt;/em> al que responderá, el nombre y el componente que mostrará dicha página o vista, además de otras muchas configuraciones que podría tener.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mi edificante experiencia ayudando a organizar la PulpoCon19</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/09/26/pulpocon-19/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/09/26/pulpocon-19/</guid><description>&lt;p>El pasado 7 de septiembre, se celebró la primera &lt;a href="https://2019.pulpocon.es">PulpoCon&lt;/a> una conferencia para programadores que he tenido el honor de ayudar a organizar.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Poco puedo añadir a la historia de como se forjó el evento a lo descrito en este &lt;em>estupendo&lt;/em> post de Rolando Caldas, que os recomiendo encarecidamente leer ⬇️⬇️⬇️⬇️⬇️&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://www.linkedin.com/pulse/la-batalla-de-organizar-pulpocon-rolando-caldas-s%C3%A1nchez/">La batalla de organizar la pulpoCon&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Sólo puedo corroborar todo lo ahí dicho y ahondar aún más en los agradecimientos a todas las personas que nos han ayudado a montar esto.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Desacoplando la interacción con una API en Vue: vue.$api</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/09/09/desacoplando-la-interaccion-con-una-api-en-vue/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/09/09/desacoplando-la-interaccion-con-una-api-en-vue/</guid><description>&lt;p>Durante el desarrollo de una web, una SPA en &lt;em>Vue&lt;/em> es muy habitual que ese desarrollo implique interactuar con una &lt;em>API&lt;/em> y lo habitual será que uses &lt;em>&lt;a href="https://github.com/axios/axios">axios&lt;/a>&lt;/em> para ello (aunque lo que voy a explicar valdría para cualquiera otra librería)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Es muy habitual que cuando necesitamos interactuar con un &lt;em>endpoint&lt;/em> de la &lt;em>API&lt;/em>, lo hagamos directamente desde el controlador, entendiendo por controlador el componente que se encarga de responder a una ruta.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Unificando la información de eventos de una comunidad: vigotech.json</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/09/02/Unificando-la-informacion-de-eventos-de-una-comunidad-vigotech-json/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/09/02/Unificando-la-informacion-de-eventos-de-una-comunidad-vigotech-json/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://vigotech.org/">VigoTech Alliance&lt;/a> la comunidad que aglutina a los grupos de tecnología de Vigo y su área de influencia, tiene entre uno de sus objetivos coordinar y divulgar las fechas de los eventos de cada uno de los grupos miembros.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En el momento de escribir esta entrada tiene 18 grupos miembros, que funcionan de forma autónoma a la hora de organizar meetups, eventos, charlas, etc, lo que hace que a la hora de mantener la información de los eventos actualizada de forma manual sea una tarea complicada.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sireno Grid: Un sistema ligero de Grid CSS, basado en Grid Layout</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/08/26/SirenoGrid-Un-sistema-ligero-de-Grid-CS-basado-en-Grid-Layout/</link><pubDate>Mon, 26 Aug 2019 12:31:08 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/08/26/SirenoGrid-Un-sistema-ligero-de-Grid-CS-basado-en-Grid-Layout/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>CSS Grid Layout&lt;/em> es un estándar del W3C que fue llevado a &lt;em>webkit&lt;/em> y &lt;em>blink&lt;/em> por &lt;a href="https://igalia.com">Igalia&lt;/a> una empresa asentada en Galicia con programadores por todo el mundo y además tuvimos el honor de organizar una charla [&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=NbeP64e8DZQ">Video&lt;/a>] de uno de los desarrolladores encargado de implementar CSS Grid Layout en Chromium/Blink y Safari/Webkit: &lt;a href="https://blogs.igalia.com/mrego/resources/">Manuel Rego&lt;/a>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Los que llevamos mucho tiempo maquetando (pero mucho, mucho), recordaremos una época en la que se maquetaba usando tablas, ¿por qué?, pues porque la mayoría de los diseños de web, se pueden &lt;em>trocear&lt;/em> en áreas o zonas cuadradas o rectangulares, algo que un su momento permitían las tablas. Con la llegada de la &lt;em>web semántica&lt;/em> y las mejoras de CSS la maquetación con tablas fue marcada como una mala práctica (que lo era). CSS Grid Layout es &amp;ldquo;como&amp;rdquo; volver a maquetar con tablas pero &lt;strong>bien&lt;/strong>. No voy a entrar en muchos detalles, pero la maquetación con tablas se definía con las etiquetas y aquí las definimos con las hojas de estilo.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Juegos Sandbox: Minecraft y 7 Days to Die (7D2D)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/08/18/Juegos-Sandbox-Minecraft-y-7-Days-to-die-7D2D/</link><pubDate>Sun, 18 Aug 2019 17:30:49 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/08/18/Juegos-Sandbox-Minecraft-y-7-Days-to-die-7D2D/</guid><description>&lt;p>Siempre me han gustado los videojuegos desde mi época del &lt;strong>Amstrad CPC464&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Como todo el mundo tengo mis géneros favoritos, y uno de ellos son los juegos de tipo &lt;em>Sandbox&lt;/em> o mundo abierto, para quien no los conozca son juegos en los que el camino del jugador no está definido por la historía, o por el programador, es decir puedes moverte por todo el mundo del juego sin más limitación que los &amp;ldquo;bordes de mapa&amp;rdquo; y puedes &lt;em>hacer lo que quieras&lt;/em> (son el límite de las acciones programadas en el juego).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mapas interactivos SVG con Vue</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/06/30/Mapas-interactivos-a-partir-de-un-SVG/</link><pubDate>Sun, 30 Jun 2019 13:17:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/06/30/Mapas-interactivos-a-partir-de-un-SVG/</guid><description>&lt;p>En un reciente proyecto me ha surgido la necesidad de crear un mapa de España interactivo en el que cada provincia fuese un elemento sobre le que poder hacer &lt;em>hover&lt;/em> y &lt;em>click&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>El proyecto lo estaba realizando el &lt;em>Nuxt.js&lt;/em> y por lo tanto en &lt;strong>Vue&lt;/strong>, por lo que decidí crear un componente que encapsulara la generación gráfica del mapa y emitiera los correspondientes eventos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lo primero que necesitamos es el mapa en formato SVG, no nos vale cualquiera debe ser un mapa en el que cada provincia esté en un path y este esté correctamente etiquetado, por ejemplo podemos usar &lt;a href="https://simplemaps.com/resources/svg-es">este&lt;/a> que es de libre tanto para uso comercial como personal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Impresiones tras un mes de uso de un teclado mecánico</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/25/Impresiones-tras-un-mes-de-uso-de-un-teclado-mecanico/</link><pubDate>Sat, 25 May 2019 17:53:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/25/Impresiones-tras-un-mes-de-uso-de-un-teclado-mecanico/</guid><description>&lt;p>Ya no se si como deformación profesional o como &amp;ldquo;tara mental&amp;rdquo; propia, siempre he sido bastante quisquilloso con los periféricos, tanto teclado como ratón, porque al fin y al cabo paso al menos 8 horas diarias usándolos y es importante sentirse cómodo con ellos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Yo trabajo principalmente en un equipo de sobremesa y hasta hace poco estaba usando el teclado de Apple, como el que se muestra en la foto (pero con layout en Español), no el &amp;ldquo;moderno&amp;rdquo; inalámbrico, sino el anterior, con cable.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mi histórico de teléfonos móviles</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/12/Mi-historico-de-telefonos-moviles/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 May 2019 10:00:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/12/Mi-historico-de-telefonos-moviles/</guid><description>&lt;p>Esta semana he decidido &amp;ldquo;jubilar&amp;rdquo; mi teléfono móvil y reemplazalo por uno más nuevo, lo que me ha hecho pensar en todos los teléfonos que he tenido y en el tiempo que me &amp;ldquo;duraban&amp;rdquo; lo me llevado a escribir este &lt;em>post&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>He de hacer notar lo &amp;ldquo;señor mayor&amp;rdquo; que me ha hecho sentir recordar conceptos ya olvidados, como el &lt;em>prepago&lt;/em>, los &lt;em>sms&lt;/em>, los tonos, etc.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;h1 id="el-primer-móvil">El primer móvil&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>&lt;figure class="image-caption">
 &lt;img
 src="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/12/Mi-historico-de-telefonos-moviles/nokia5110_hu_be87ccead4a09b13.jpg"
 alt=""
 title=""
 width="1100"
 height="1217" srcset="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/12/Mi-historico-de-telefonos-moviles/nokia5110_hu_da727c0e0f69bf72.webp 458w, https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/12/Mi-historico-de-telefonos-moviles/nokia5110_hu_84af53e2591acfd9.webp 768w, https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/12/Mi-historico-de-telefonos-moviles/nokia5110_hu_c49367042d34703b.webp 1200w" sizes="(max-width: 458px) 100vw, (max-width: 768px) 100vw, (max-width: 1200px) 100vw"/>
 &lt;figcaption>&lt;/figcaption>
 &lt;/figure>
(Foto: &lt;a href="https://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:CSIRO_ScienceImage_2936_Nokia_mobile_phone.jpg">Wikimedia&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Haciendo café: simple análisis de costes</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/04/27/haciendo-cafe/</link><pubDate>Sat, 27 Apr 2019 11:44:20 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/04/27/haciendo-cafe/</guid><description>&lt;p>Aunque no me puedo considerar un gran &amp;ldquo;cafetero&amp;rdquo;, si que me gusta desayunar con un buen café por las mañanas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hasta hace unos años las opciones para hacer casé no eran muchas: Cafetera de goteo, cafetera italiana y poco más. (Algunas opciones más tendríamos por eso me centraré en comentar las más habituales). Pero desde la aparición en el mercado de las Cápsulas monodosis, estas han copado el mercado, ya sean Nespresso, Senseo, Dolce Gusto, Tassimo, etc.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>No todo es trabajar: Jugando con trenes</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/04/20/no-todo-es-trabajar-jugando-con-trenes/</link><pubDate>Sat, 20 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/04/20/no-todo-es-trabajar-jugando-con-trenes/</guid><description>&lt;p>No todo es siempre trabajar, los momentos de ocio tambíen son importantes.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>De pequeño tuve un maqueta funcional de un tren eléctrico, que desgraciadamente, por lo que más la recuerdo es por que nunca llegó a funcionar correctamente, problemas con los engranajes de transmisión, que por más que se pidieron recambios nunca se resolvieron.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Con los años y con el desarrollo lúdico de la informática, fueron apareciendo juegos &amp;ldquo;de trenes&amp;rdquo; que suplieron, con creces, ese trauma infantil.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Accediendo al Sergas y a eSaude desde linux</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/04/07/Accediendo-al-Sergas-y-al-eSaude-desde-linux/</link><pubDate>Sun, 07 Apr 2019 19:26:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/04/07/Accediendo-al-Sergas-y-al-eSaude-desde-linux/</guid><description>&lt;p>Debido mi ya no tan
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/08/Cosas-que-he-aprendido-de-un-cancer/">reciente enfermedad&lt;/a>
, y dedicado tiempo a acceder a la página web del &lt;a href="https://www.sergas.es/">Sergas&lt;/a> (Servizo Galego de Saúde) para usar un servicio que fue &lt;a href="https://www.farodevigo.es/gran-vigo/2016/05/11/sergas-lanza-app-consultar-tratamientos/1458511.html">presentado en 2016&lt;/a>, y que desde &lt;a href="https://www.lavozdegalicia.es/noticia/galicia/2018/12/17/puede-consultar-pruebas-medicas-internet/0003_201812G17P49913.htm">finales de 2018&lt;/a> permite acceder a la función, que yo creo que útil, de descarga de las pruebas diagnosticas de imagen: TACs, resonancias, radiografías, ecografías, etc&amp;hellip;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Para acceder a esta herramienta es necesario disponer de eDNI, Chave365 o de un certificado digital, pero en este último caso es necesario pasar antes por el Centro de Salud para autorizar a dicho certificado a darnos acceso a nuestros datos de Salud, un paso que no entiendo del todo, puesto que para obtener un certificado de la FNMT, debemos verificar nuestra identidad.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mis proyectos Open Source</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/03/31/Mis-proyectos-Open-Source/</link><pubDate>Sun, 31 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/03/31/Mis-proyectos-Open-Source/</guid><description>&lt;p>En todos estos años &lt;em>&amp;ldquo;haciendo cosas con el ordenador&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em>, he aprendido que compartir conocimiento y código es una muy buena forma de devolver una pequeña parte de lo recibido, por que al fin y al cabo en mi caso el 90% del software que uso para desarrollar, ya sean herramientas, frameworks, librerias o el propio lenguaje son &lt;em>Open Source&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He aquí una lista de los proyectos que liberado agrupados por de una forma totalmente arbitraria.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mis charlas</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/03/01/mis-charlas/</link><pubDate>Fri, 01 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/03/01/mis-charlas/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hace un par de años, superando mi timidez, empecé a dar &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->chapas&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> charlas técnicas en publico, obviamente la primera fue un desastre &amp;#x1f613;, pero para eso es la primera, para aprender, y tambíen la segunda y la tercera&amp;hellip;. &amp;#x1f602;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Compartir conocimiento de esta forma, es algo que recomiendo, por muchos motivos, incluso motivos &amp;ldquo;egoístas&amp;rdquo; como el hecho de obligarte a esforzate a preparar ese tema sobre el que vas a hablar.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>"Domotizar" una lámpara de escritorio por 10€</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/02/04/lampara-de-escritorio-domotica/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/02/04/lampara-de-escritorio-domotica/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;figure class="image-caption">
 &lt;img
 src="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/02/04/lampara-de-escritorio-domotica/sonoff_hu_303b580423f3e6b.jpg"
 alt=""
 title=""
 width="1100"
 height="828" srcset="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/02/04/lampara-de-escritorio-domotica/sonoff_hu_90bf86f3cd632ae3.webp 458w, https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/02/04/lampara-de-escritorio-domotica/sonoff_hu_2b38f7ab67d8f87e.webp 833w" sizes="(max-width: 458px) 100vw, 833px"/>
 &lt;figcaption>&lt;/figcaption>
 &lt;/figure>
Hace ya unos cuantos meses había comprado &lt;a href="https://amzn.to/2HDOlWM">este aparatillo&lt;/a>: un interruptor wifi, con la intención de probar a &amp;ldquo;domotizar&amp;rdquo; algo en casa.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Este modelo concreto es de doble canal por lo que lleva dos interruptores en el mismo aparato, pero para este proyecto con un sólo canal es suficiente.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Como la mayoría de estos aparatos de bajo coste están basado en el &lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/ESP8266">chip ESP8266&lt;/a> usado originalmente para dotar de conectividad wifi a los Arduino, pero que ha demostrado su solvencia usado de forma independiente.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mi experiencia con el trato médico-paciente</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/01/28/mi-experiencia-con-el-trato-medico-paciente/</link><pubDate>Mon, 28 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/01/28/mi-experiencia-con-el-trato-medico-paciente/</guid><description>&lt;p>Aclarar de antemano que esta entrada no pretende ser una magufada que ponga por delante la parte psicológica a la médica, si en algún momento parece eso, lo he escrito muy mal &amp;#x1f602;&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Por diversos motivos, ya desde pequeño he tenido que estar varias veces ingresado en hospitales, y eso me ha permitido ver desde el punto de vista del paciente la evolución del funcionamiento de un hospital y del trato al paciente.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Una prueba radiológica (PET-CT), un friki (Yo) y un contador Geiger</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/29/Una-prueba-radiologica-PET-CT-un-friki-Yo-y-un-contador-Geiger/</link><pubDate>Sat, 29 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/29/Una-prueba-radiologica-PET-CT-un-friki-Yo-y-un-contador-Geiger/</guid><description>&lt;p>El pasado día 26 de diciembre, tenia programada una prueba radiológica para hacer un seguimiento del linfoma. Esta prueba era un PET-CT, en castellano: &lt;strong>&lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tomograf%C3%ADa_por_emisi%C3%B3n_de_positrones">tomografía por emisión de positrones&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> es una de las prueba más avanzadas actualmente para detectar las células tumorales y su ubicación en el cuerpo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La prueba &lt;strong>no invasiva&lt;/strong> y consiste en inyectar al paciente (yo) un &lt;em>radiofármaco&lt;/em>, y mediante un detector observar que partes del cuerpo tienen un metabolismo más rápido, estas nos indicarán donde están las células tumorales.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Como es uno de mis "ciclos" de quimioterapia</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/20/Como-es-uno-de-mis-ciclos-de-quimioterapia/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Dec 2018 10:34:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/20/Como-es-uno-de-mis-ciclos-de-quimioterapia/</guid><description>&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Antes de nada aclarar que lo que cuento esta basado en mi experiencia personal, no pretende ser ni una referencia, ni consejos para otras personas.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;p>Como ya comenté en la anterior entrada, cada vez que te &amp;ldquo;ponen&amp;rdquo; el tratamiento de quimioterapia se le denomina ciclo, en mi caso es cada 21 días.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Os voy a contar cómo es uno de mis ciclos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En primer paso es acudir temprano 8:00-8:40 al hospital de día, allí te hacen una extracción de sangre para un análisis marcado por la oncóloga como urgente, en este análisis se &amp;ldquo;mide&amp;rdquo;:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cosas que he aprendido de un cáncer</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/08/Cosas-que-he-aprendido-de-un-cancer/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/12/08/Cosas-que-he-aprendido-de-un-cancer/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hace unos meses me han diagnosticado un cáncer, un &lt;em>Linfoma no Hodgkin difuso de células B grandes&lt;/em>. Ahora mismo estoy a mitad de tratamiento y me gustaría compartir lo que he aprendido durante este tiempo.&lt;/p>
&lt;blockquote>
&lt;p>Antes de nada aclarar que lo que cuento esta basado en mi experiencia personal, no pretende ser ni una referencia, ni consejos para otras personas.&lt;/p>
&lt;/blockquote>
&lt;ol>
&lt;li>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>La palabra &lt;em>cáncer&lt;/em> incluye cientos de distintos tipos&lt;/strong> y subtipos, lo que implica síntomas, riesgos, complicaciones y tratamientos distintos (muy distintos unos de otros). Aunque la base de la enfermedad es la mismas (una reproducción anormal y sin control de las células tumorales), dependiendo de qué celúlas sean y donde estén situadas es como si fuese una enfermedad distinta.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mis canales favoritos de YouTube</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/11/29/Mis-canales-favoritos-de-YouTube/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/11/29/Mis-canales-favoritos-de-YouTube/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hago una seleccion de canales de YouTube interesantes a los que estoy suscrito. No estan todos, bien por que no los considero relevantes o por que hace mucho tiempo que no publican nada&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="ciencia-y-divulgación">Ciencia y divulgación:&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCbdSYaPD-lr1kW27UJuk8Pw">QuantumFracture&lt;/a>
¡Ciencia! ¡y con animaciones! El lado más loco (y real) del Universo.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCMbQbVilo-nezMvwf1BZfAA">Ciencia de sofá&lt;/a>
Divulgación científica para mentes distraídas.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCa3DVlGH2_QhvwuWlPa6MDQ">Jaime Altozano&lt;/a>
Todo sobre música. Cómo funciona, por qué es como es.Canal para entender lo que oyes.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCGKzjVZGdJ0YmUqg42xfO5w">Antroporama&lt;/a>
Divulgación científica sobre el Ser Humano, nuestra conducta, mente y nuestro secreto mejor guardado: el cerebro.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCoXtmmnLCbXDiSo8GxsmOzA">La gata de Schrödinger&lt;/a>
Canal de divulgación de la ciencia desde una perspectiva escéptica y con un toque de humor.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCMnPZh6PyA5PSYoNt0cjuxg">Minuto de física&lt;/a>
En pocas palabras: física genial y ciencia interesante&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCibUX4QoSrRwmBZf0Ig-OCg">Deborah Ciencia&lt;/a>
Química, divulgadora científica y especialista en arte contemporáneo.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC6nSFpj9HTCZ5t-N3Rm3-HA">Vsauce&lt;/a> &lt;em>ENG&lt;/em>
Divulgación cientifica y espirito curioso.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCq3HgwV38l3WCHx8nyFtc6A">Carolina Jiménez&lt;/a>
Artista de VFX especializada en Layout para cine internacional.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC7DdEm33SyaTDtWYGO2CwdA">Physics Girl&lt;/a> &lt;em>ENG&lt;/em>
Ciencia aplicada&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCns-8DssCBba7M4nu7wk7Aw/videos">Date un voltio&lt;/a> y &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCQX_MZRCaluNKxkywkLEgfA">Date un vlog&lt;/a>
Divulgaciópn física por Javier Santaolalla.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="gamming">Gamming&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCWktmlIWDDxOYSmV7gRV9gw">Buck Fernandez&lt;/a>
Especializado en juegos de &lt;em>survival&lt;/em>.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCjuRnAVSiarRGOI8DA2oJtQ">Menos Trece&lt;/a>
Juegos de todo tipo.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCRl7gGf5iPTeVrzxx0jEWMA">Vicio One More Time&lt;/a>
Juegos de todo tipo, y muchos de ellos curiosos y en partidas compartidas&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC3gdaplfyzSr2YjHHwxRhPQ">Heikki360ES&lt;/a>
SimRacing en estado puro&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="formula-1">Formula 1&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCB_qr75-ydFVKSF9Dmo6izg">Formula 1&lt;/a>
Canal oficial de la F1&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC89aCe0fFyScFU-NegT2CFQ">Efeuno&lt;/a>
Canal de opinión y resumenes de carreras.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="programación--técnica">Programación / Técnica&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCAJALvsCWz8Kh6wOySHUJAA">Drupal Association&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCPOAykv_UgFa79_mub4Orbw">Carlos Buenosvinos Zamora&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCIpArN21nIT2lvZX-nkjP7A">Igalia&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCeqrsQm33UBFHb50zorReHQ">RootedCON&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="general">General&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCP92h2vCD3hw1xbNqIGY2RQ">Saul Lopez&lt;/a>
Coche electrico y movilidad sostenible, desde el punto de vista de un propietario de un Tesla Model S que cuenta curiosidades de su coche.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCUK0HBIBWgM2c4vsPhkYY4w">The Slow Mo Guys&lt;/a>
Básicamente explosiones a cámara super, super lenta.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCvph04Sh9CFKAw-gA6y-brQ">I_am_puma&lt;/a>
Una parejas rusa comparte su piso con un Puma llamado Месси (Messi)&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCCNgRIfWQKZyPkNvHEzPh7Q">Ter&lt;/a>
De este canal me quedo sólo con los videos de arquitectura.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCF-d8KqwHpedg5IN1RqxURQ">David Bravo&lt;/a>
Canal del conocido abogado David Bravo.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCtJVZjY6xsZUV-sYdcIFpZw">331Erock&lt;/a>
Creador de versiones metal de temas conocidos.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="humor">Humor&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCPu5nstS7cbx_GUiH-kxwVw">Pantomima full&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC6lJZ9Ctx1vcmRY9cFEPyww">La vida moderna&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCvosUrZ7hXpzAyobhfztg4w">La resistencia&lt;/a>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCLRdisr7nBPa1PzyvB8LkXA">Nadie sabe nada&lt;/a>
Improvisación y humor entre Buenafuente y Berto.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCXUVqP5eE3DGCrFz_TRyOdQ">Zorman&lt;/a>
Principamente videos musicales paridiando &amp;ldquo;tribus urbanas&amp;rdquo;&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCAqznKuq5g6a0a8nRDXaXPA">Loulogio&lt;/a>
Humor y reviews de pelis&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="compilations">Compilations&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCk_e9rhSH_Gg4Mp44Ut72ZQ">Win Compilation&lt;/a>
Recopilaciones mensuales de videos de &lt;em>Wins&lt;/em>&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCPIvT-zcQl2H0vabdXJGcpg">The Pet Collective&lt;/a>
Videos de gatetes, perreros, monetes, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul>
&lt;h2 id="varios">Varios&lt;/h2>
&lt;ul>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCm9K6rby98W8JigLoZOh6FQ">LockPickingLayer&lt;/a>
Prueba detalladas de cerraduras, candados, etc.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCMrKscEv_Ri1pvlRsLxsqJQ">Stop a Douchebag&lt;/a>
Rusos intentando evitar que otros rusos usen las aceras para circular en coche.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UC9suRmwQRSSBFOG7Mus1S_g">Vicisitud y sordidez&lt;/a>
No sabría como definir este canal. Destaco especialmente este video &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k-ZrzH9qorw">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=k-ZrzH9qorw&lt;/a> que todo buen vigués debería conocer.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCP4R4OAJXEwnNOE28P8ophw">Nuclear Vault&lt;/a>
Videos desclasificados de pruebas nucleares.&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCewve_DY_atXyU1wb9jWEBA">Krzysztof Smejlis&lt;/a>
Videos de dos gatetes (Bobo y Nikita).&lt;/li>
&lt;li>&lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCcZBuBZ7Cp7skPRn87AY2Ew">Video Buck&lt;/a>
Reviews de pelis, especialmente ochenteras.&lt;/li>
&lt;/ul></description></item><item><title>Generación de números de cancelación de factura para Drupal Commerce</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/01/22/generacion-de-numeros-de-cancelacion-de-factura-para-drupal-commerce/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/01/22/generacion-de-numeros-de-cancelacion-de-factura-para-drupal-commerce/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recientemente a uno de nuestros clientes para el cual hemos diseñado, y programado una tienda online, empleando para ello Drupal 7 y &lt;a href="https://drupalcommerce.org/">Drupal commerce&lt;/a>, le surgieron varias necesidades relativas a la facturación.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En primer lugar necesitaba que los pedidos generasen automáticamente una serie de números de factura por cada año, de la forma **2018-123, 2018-124, &amp;hellip; **Hasta aquí todo normal, uno de los módulos contribuidos de &lt;em>Drupal Commerce&lt;/em>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Este módulo se llama &lt;a href="https://www.drupal.org/project/commerce_billy">Commerce Billy&lt;/a>, y cumple esta necesidad, además de proporcionarnos la generación de facturas en PDF,  posibilidad de facturación automática o manual, y un largo etc de pequeñas pero útiles funcionalidades relativas a la facturación.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>He dejado de usar Facebook. ¿Y ahora qué?</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/01/05/he-dejado-facebook/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2018/01/05/he-dejado-facebook/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Respuesta larga (TL;DR)&lt;/strong>:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Entre en Facebook el 31 de diciembre de 2008 (casi 10 años ya) pero hace tiempo que  ya no me proporcionaba lo que hacia en su momento, una forma de conectar y de compartir momentos interesantes con mis conocidos, amigos y allegados, sino que se había convertido en un multitudinario monólogo múltiple.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He de decir que todos los años por estas fechas tenia la costumbre de revisar mis contactos y eliminar sin pudor aquellas personas con las que no había tenido contacto en la propia plataforma (ni un comentario, ni un like, ni un chat en varios meses) ya que no tiene mucho sentido estar &amp;ldquo;ligado&amp;rdquo; a una persona con la que no tienes ni un mínimo de interacción.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Abstraer los datos de su representación en un CMS = WIN</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/2017/abstraer-los-datos-de-su-representacion-en-un-cms-win/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/2017/abstraer-los-datos-de-su-representacion-en-un-cms-win/</guid><description>&lt;p>Tanto en desarrollo web como en otras muchas áreas la &lt;strong>abstracción&lt;/strong> es fundamental para poder avanzar sin necesidad de estar pensando en cada uno de los niveles de complejidad. La &lt;a href="https://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abstracci%C3%B3n_%28inform%C3%A1tica%29">&lt;strong>abstracción&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> básicamente consiste en aislar un elemento de su contexto.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Si has leído el título del &lt;em>post&lt;/em>, te habrá dado cuenta de que vamos a hablar de &lt;strong>abstracción de contenido&lt;/strong> respecto a la **representación (**que tendrá para el visitante de la web), por ejemplo esto es que el campo fecha  (de un artículo), no lo tenga que insertar el autor junto con el resto del texto. Lo mismo que el título, las imágenes o cualquier otro elemento.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Crear plantillas de email con nuxt.js</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/10/23/crear-plantillas-de-email-con-nuxtjs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Oct 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/10/23/crear-plantillas-de-email-con-nuxtjs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Si eres maquetador Web y quieres viajar al pasado, a un pasado en el que se maquetaban las webs usando tablas anidas hasta el infinito, imágenes de 1x1px transparentes, la etiqueta &lt;strong>&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->&lt;/strong>, &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --> en lugar de &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted -->, y un largo ecéteras de cosas que me ponen los pelos de punta.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Como, probablemente has podido extraer de mis palabras, para mi es una pesadilla. maquetar una plantailla de email, por que es como si de golpe te quitasen todas las herramientas que tienes para hacerlo y con un martillo y cincel, por eso trato siemple de simplificar lo máximo posible el trabajo buscnado métodos que me permitan que la tarea de maquetar un email tengoa un poco de &lt;em>dignidad&lt;/em> ;).&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>¿Por qué el directorio home en linux se representa con ~ (tilde)?</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/06/13/por-que-el-directorio-home-en-linux-se-representa-con-tilde/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/06/13/por-que-el-directorio-home-en-linux-se-representa-con-tilde/</guid><description>&lt;p>Cuando comencé a dar mis primeros pasos en Linux me llamó la atención que si quería cambiar a mi directorio home, lo podía hacer de &amp;ldquo;la forma larga&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>$ cd /home/usuario
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>O usando ~ (lo que los anglosajones llaman &lt;em>tilde&lt;/em>)&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>$ cd ~/
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>lo que era un ahorro de escritura y la mayor ventaja que un script funcionaria para cualquier usuario.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://sergiocarracedo.es/images/l3esv.jpg"alt="" title="" />&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Alguna vez me pregunte cual era el origen del uso de este carácter, pero nunca investigué mucho más, hasta que hace unos días encontré esta explicación en https://unix.stackexchange.com/questions/34196/why-was-chosen-to-represent-the-home-directory/34198#34198 que no deja de ser curiosa y traduzco de forma libre &amp;ldquo;En los sistemas operativos tipo Unix, la tilde significa el directorio home, una practica derivada de la Terminal &lt;strong>Lear-Siegler ADM-3A&lt;/strong> muy común en los 70s que en la misma tecla aparecía la &lt;em>tilde&lt;/em> y la inscripción _HOME _que servia para ir a la parte superior de la pantalla.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Usar un 'field widget' en un formulario convencional en Drupal 7</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/06/08/usar-un-field-widget-en-un-formulario-convencional-en-drupal-7/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/06/08/usar-un-field-widget-en-un-formulario-convencional-en-drupal-7/</guid><description>&lt;p>El &lt;a href="https://api.drupal.org/api/drupal/developer%21topics%21forms_api_reference.html/7.x">Form API&lt;/a> de Drupal es muy potente, para mí es algo, que cuando programo sobre otros &lt;em>CMS&lt;/em> o &lt;em>frameworks&lt;/em> echo mucho en falta, por que Drupal ha conseguido que la laboriosa tarea de crear, validar, y securizar formularios, quede reducida a un &amp;ldquo;simple&amp;rdquo; array.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Este Form API dispone de unos tipos, que yo denominaría primitivos, y no porque&amp;rsquo;estén anticuados, si no por que a partir de ellos se pueden crear construcciones más complejas, como hace el módulo &lt;a href="https://api.drupal.org/api/drupal/modules%21field%21field.module/group/field/7.x">Field&lt;/a>, más concretamente su submódulo &lt;a href="https://api.drupal.org/api/drupal/modules!field_ui!field_ui.module/7.x">Field UI&lt;/a>, que como ya sabréis es el que nos facilita la creación de los distintos tipos de campos, por ejemplo en la creación de contenido. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Recibir notificaciones de acceso SSH desde una IP desconocida</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/05/18/recibir-notificaciones-de-acceso-ssh-desde-una-ip-desconocida/</link><pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/05/18/recibir-notificaciones-de-acceso-ssh-desde-una-ip-desconocida/</guid><description>&lt;p>Es habitual que administremos o accedamos de una u otra forma a máquina remotas mediante SSH, ya sea mediante contraseña o &lt;em>key&lt;/em> (muy recomendado), pero el acceso remoto es una vulnerabilidad en si misma, o al menos es un posible punto de entrada de un atacante o individuo malicioso. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lo habitual es disponer de &lt;strong>&lt;em>fail2ban&lt;/em>&lt;/strong> sobre el servicio &lt;em>sshd&lt;/em> que evite los ataques de fuerza bruta.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pero además, puede ser muy interesante recibir una notificación (SMS, email, Push, etc&amp;hellip;) cada vez que se produzca un login correcto en el sistema mediante &lt;em>ssh&lt;/em>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vigo hace piña</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/05/04/vigo-hace-pina/</link><pubDate>Thu, 04 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/05/04/vigo-hace-pina/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hace un par de meses, comentaba que 
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/03/algo-se-mueve-en-vigo/">&amp;ldquo;algo se movía&amp;rdquo; en Vigo&lt;/a>
, que las comunidades de desarrolladores, y en general técnicas, comenzaban aparecer y crecer.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Pues bien, esto &lt;strong>pasa al siguiente nivel&lt;/strong>: de la mundana necesidad de coordinar los espacios y las fechas de los &lt;em>meetups&lt;/em> de los distintos grupos, ha surgido algo más, algo que personalmente me ilusiona mucho, por que siempre es bonito ver crecer algo, una idea, pero más si uno es participe aunque sea en una pequeña proporción.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Usando Vue.js + electron.js para crear aplicaciones de escritorio</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/18/usando-vuejs-electronjs-para-crear-aplicaciones-de-escritorio/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/18/usando-vuejs-electronjs-para-crear-aplicaciones-de-escritorio/</guid><description>&lt;p>**&lt;a href="https://electron.atom.io/">Electron.js&lt;/a> **es &lt;em>framework&lt;/em> pensado para crear aplicaciones &amp;ldquo;nativas&amp;rdquo; de escritorio usando JavaScript, HTML y CSS. Básicamente ejecuta tu código en &lt;strong>node.js&lt;/strong> y realiza el render de la app en &lt;a href="https://www.chromium.org/">Chromium&lt;/a>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Este detalle lo debemos tener muy en cuenta: por un lado tenemos un proceso (&lt;strong>main process&lt;/strong>) que es como su nombre indica el proceso principal de la aplicación, y que mientras este ejecutándose, nuestra aplicación esta funcionando. El &lt;strong>Main process&lt;/strong>, no tiene visualización, es decir, &lt;strong>no&lt;/strong> es la ventana principal, pero si que una de sis funciones es crear la ventana o ventanas de nuestra aplicación, y esto nos lleva a la segunda pieza; el/los procesos de render (&lt;strong>Renderer process&lt;/strong>), cada ventana que cree (no tiene por que visualizarse en ese momento) crea una instancia de &lt;em>Chormium&lt;/em> que corre en su propio proceso.y de forma independiente a las demás. Cada una de estos procesos (&lt;em>renderer process&lt;/em>) unicamente puede comunicarse con el &lt;em>main&lt;/em>, no hay posibilidad de comunicación &lt;strong>directa&lt;/strong> entre &lt;em>renderers&lt;/em>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vuex el Redux de Vue.js (II)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/06/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-ii/</link><pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/06/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-ii/</guid><description>&lt;p>En la
&lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/03/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-i/">primera parte&lt;/a>
, expliqué algunos de los conceptos básicos de **vuex: **El **state, ** los &lt;strong>getters&lt;/strong> y las &lt;strong>mutations&lt;/strong>. Si recuerdas, el paradigma de una &lt;em>librería de control del patrón de estado&lt;/em> como &lt;strong>vuex&lt;/strong> es mantener el &lt;em>state&lt;/em> como única fuente de verdad, y para ello los valores del estado solo pueden ser modificados mediante &lt;em>mutations&lt;/em>, que deben ser además &lt;strong>síncronas&lt;/strong>. Si necesitamos hacer &amp;ldquo;cambios&amp;rdquo; de forma asíncrona podemos hacer uso de las &lt;strong>acciones / actions.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Vuex el Redux de Vue.js (I)</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/03/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-i/</link><pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/04/03/vuex-el-redux-de-vuejs-i/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;a href="https://vuex.vuejs.org/en/">&lt;strong>Vuex&lt;/strong>&lt;/a> se define a si mismo como una &lt;em>librería de control del patrón de estado.&lt;/em> Veremos lo que implica este patrón, pero antes veamos los conceptos básicos:&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="estado-state">Estado (state)&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>El estado es un objeto plano, este contiene los valores que definen tu aplicación en un momento dado. Es la &lt;strong>única fuente de verdad&lt;/strong>, es decir, es el único lugar donde consultar estos valores. Aclarar que el estado es el conjunto de valores que usa la aplicación para reaccionar como lo hace en un momento determinado, por ejemplo, si estamos mostrando una lista de &lt;em>posts de blog&lt;/em>, esta lista es parte del estado, la página que estamos viendo es otra parte del estado. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Introducción a Vue.js</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/15/introduccion-vuejs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/15/introduccion-vuejs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Desde hace unos años han aparecido multitud de librerías y frameworks javascript para el desarrollo de aplicaciones frontend, facilitado por el aumento de rendimiento y velocidad de &lt;em>javascript&lt;/em> en los navegadores modernos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Existe una variedad, que yo definiria como excesiva, de frameworks JS. Entre los más famosos o extendidos estan &lt;em>Angular.js, Angular2, React.js, Ember.js&lt;/em>, y también el objeto de este post: &lt;strong>Vue.js&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;strong>Vue.js&lt;/strong> se define a si mismo como &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Intuitivo, rápido y por componentes MVVM para construir interfaces interactivas&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; (podéis saber más sobre el patrón Model-View-Viewmodel aquí: &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93viewmodel">https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Model%E2%80%93view%E2%80%93viewmodel&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Entidad con propietario en Laravel 5.4</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/07/entidad-con-propietario-en-laravel-54/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/07/entidad-con-propietario-en-laravel-54/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recientemente he iniciado un proyecto con &lt;strong>Laravel 5.4&lt;/strong>, en el que algunos de mis modelos tienen un propietario, es decir, los crea un usuario y sólo el tiene acceso para ver o editar los datos de su entidad.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La forma más simple que he encontrado es hacer uso de las posiblilidades que Laravel nos ofrece mediante los &lt;em>middleware.&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En primer lugar extendemos el &lt;em>Model&lt;/em> que nos provee &lt;em>Elocuent&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>&amp;lt;?php

namespace App;
use Illuminate\Database\Eloquent\Model;

class OwnableModel extends Model {

 public function getOwnerId() {
 return isset($this-&amp;gt;user_id) ? $this-&amp;gt;user_id : null;
 }

 public function checkIsOwner($user_id) {
 return $this-&amp;gt;getOwnerId() == $user_id;
 }
}
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Esta clase tiene dos métodos: &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Algo se mueve en Vigo</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/03/algo-se-mueve-en-vigo/</link><pubDate>Fri, 03 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2017/03/03/algo-se-mueve-en-vigo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Como algunos sabreis hace poco más de un año &lt;a href="http://felixgomez.eu/">Félix Gómez&lt;/a> y yo creamos la comunidad de desarrolladores &lt;a href="http://www.phpvigo.com">PHPVigo&lt;/a>. El objectivo, mediante eventos mensuales, es conocer a otros desarrolladores, compartir conocimiento mediante charlas y principalmente crear comunidad, una comunidad que unida pueda demostrar que desde Vigo, desde Galicia, hay personas y empresas desarrollando proyectos y técnologías que nada tiene que envidiar a otras partes del mundo, como ha sucedido recientemente con Rubén González que a raíz de preparar una charla para PHPVigo, descubrió &lt;a href="http://symfony.es/noticias/2017/02/27/composer-reduce-su-consumo-de-memoria-hasta-un-30-gracias-a-un-programador-espanol/">como reducir hasta un 30% el uso de memoria de composer&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Backup de archivos que no estan en un repo GIT</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2016/12/28/backup-de-archivos-que-no-estan-en-un-repo-git/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2016/12/28/backup-de-archivos-que-no-estan-en-un-repo-git/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recientemente me surgió la necesidad de &lt;strong>optimizar el espacio&lt;/strong> requerido para los &lt;strong>backups&lt;/strong> de mi equipo de trabajo. Principalmente son sitios web y actualmente volcaba todas las carperas de proyectos a otro disco y a &lt;strong>Dropbox&lt;/strong>, pero Dropbox tiene un grave problema de rendimiento indexando gran cantidad de archivos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Analizando el proceso de backup y hablando con otros programadores sobre su forma de hacer backups, me di cuenta que una parte del problema ya la tenia resuelta de antemano: &lt;strong>GIT&lt;/strong>. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Módulo Drupal 7: Cuenta atras lanzamiento website</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2016/09/12/modulo-drupal-7-cuenta-atras-lanzamiento-website/</link><pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2016/09/12/modulo-drupal-7-cuenta-atras-lanzamiento-website/</guid><description>&lt;p>En más de una ocasión nos ha sucedido que una vez finalizado el trabajo en un sitio web, el cliente solicita que este no se publique de forma instantanea, si no que aparezca una página en la que se muestre una &lt;strong>cuenta atrás&lt;/strong> y que una vez esta cuenta llege a 0 el site este online. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Tradicionalmente esto lo realizabamos de forma manual, pero tiene bastantes desventajas, como tener que estar pendiente de hacer la publicación del sitio. Por ello decidimos crear un &lt;strong>módulo para Drupal 7&lt;/strong> que permitiese hacer esta tarea de forma &lt;strong>automática&lt;/strong> y que además fuese facil de gestionar por el cliente llegado el caso de que necesitase ajustar la fecha límite de la cuenta atrás.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Circuitos de Formula 1 (2016) en Google Maps</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2016/03/01/circuitos-de-formula-1-2016-en-google-maps/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2016/03/01/circuitos-de-formula-1-2016-en-google-maps/</guid><description>&lt;p>Como fan de la Formula 1 que soy, simpre me ha gustado conocer y ver los circuitos más allá de lo que las televisiones nos ofrecen, que es una visión muy centrada en el circuito.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Gracias a Google Maps podemos llegar a cada uno de los circuitos del Mundial, ver su entorno y en algunos casos el Street View dentro de los propios ciruitos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Me llaman la atención algunos circuitos, como por ejemplo Albert Park, un circuito semi-urbano que se disputa sobre las propias carreteras que atraviesan el parque y que es completamente desmontado una vez finalizado el evento de F1 y otras pruebas que se disputan en el. Si accedemos al &lt;a href="https://www.google.es/maps/@-37.8510026,144.9701528,3a,75y,322.42h,76.35t/data=!3m6!1e1!3m4!1sBhEeanq0JWq2Zydb_XXNKg!2e0!7i13312!8i6656">Street View&lt;/a> del circuito, cuesta en algunos tramos reconocer la pista sin las vallas de seguridad.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Despliegue usando Deployer</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2015/10/29/despliegue-usando-deployer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Oct 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2015/10/29/despliegue-usando-deployer/</guid><description>&lt;p>Desde el momento que ponemos un sistema en producción y necesitamos mantener el código o continuar el desarrollo surge una tediosa tarea, subir los cambios al servidor de producción. Esto normalmente lo hacemos empleando un FTP mediante el cual subimos los ficheros modificados. Pero ahi esta el &amp;ldquo;problema&amp;rdquo;, en muchos casos conocer los ficheros que se han modificado (aunque lo podemos hacer empleando &lt;em>git&lt;/em> y comparando &lt;em>commits&lt;/em> para obtener una lista de archivos cambiados) y una vez que los conocemos debemos subir a mano los ficheros modificados. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sirve tu página 404 como estática en Drupal</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2015/02/05/sirve-tu-pagina-404-como-estatica-en-drupal/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Feb 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2015/02/05/sirve-tu-pagina-404-como-estatica-en-drupal/</guid><description>&lt;p>En la configuración estándar de &lt;strong>Drupal&lt;/strong> este trata de absorber todo el tráfico que se genera contra el directorio (y subdirectorios) donde esta instalado en el servidor, esto incluye también a los errores 404. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cualquier solicitud de un fichero que no exista &lt;strong>Drupal&lt;/strong> la gestionará en un nuevo dominio esto no es un problema ya que, en teoría, la mayoría de los errores 404 se deberán a errores de escritura en las rutas por parte de los usuarios, pero en un sitio con alto tráfico  que acabamos de remodelar y en el que no están correctamente creadas las redirecciones desde la antiguas rutas a la nuevas podemos encontrarnos con que estamos sirviendo muchas &lt;strong>páginas 404&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>El uso de &amp;#039;//&amp;#039; como comodín para &amp;#039;http://&amp;#039; y &amp;#039;https://&amp;#039;</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2013/01/21/el-uso-de-como-comodin-para-http-y-https/</link><pubDate>Mon, 21 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2013/01/21/el-uso-de-como-comodin-para-http-y-https/</guid><description>&lt;p>Crear una web que pueda ser navegable mediante http y https normalmente supone tener algún tipo de variable  o modificador en el lenguaje que genere la salida HTML del website, por ejemplo PHP para que las peticiones de los recursos, como CSS, JS, imágenes, etc se realicen mediante el protocolo correcto.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Por ejemplo si estamos navegando por una web en http:// (modo no encriptado) y pedimos una imagen mediante &lt;em>http&lt;strong>s&lt;/strong>://&lt;a href="http://www.misitio.com/imagen.png">www.misitio.com/imagen.png&lt;/a>&lt;/em>  en principio puede parecer que no deberíamos tener ningún problema, pero si la red del visitante filtra el puerto 443 (https) cosa que sucede en algunas empresas (cada vez menos) no podría acceder al recurso, si el recurso que solicitamos (que no coincide en protocolo) necesita hacer uso de alguna cookie, dependiendo de como este configurada esta podría no poder acceder a ella.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Visualiza gráficamente tus expresiones regulares: regexper.com</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2013/01/07/visualiza-graficamente-tus-expresiones-regulares-regexpercom/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Jan 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2013/01/07/visualiza-graficamente-tus-expresiones-regulares-regexpercom/</guid><description>&lt;p>Las &lt;a href="http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Expresi%C3%B3n_regular">expresiones regulares&lt;/a> en cualquier lenguaje de programación son muy útiles y potentes, ahorrándonos escribir muchas lineas de código. Si la expresión es sencilla, nos va a ser fácil como humanos comprenderla de un vistazo, pero si  la expresión se complica, si no la hemos creado nosotros, o si ya ha pasado tiempo desde que lo hemos hecho, puede ser un poco más complicado entender lo que hace o para que nos sirve.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bigdump: Importa grandes ficheros mysql sin problemas</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/11/29/bigdump-importa-grandes-ficheros-mysql-sin-problemas/</link><pubDate>Thu, 29 Nov 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/11/29/bigdump-importa-grandes-ficheros-mysql-sin-problemas/</guid><description>&lt;p>Una de las pesadillas de los desarrolladores web (a menos es una de las mías) es encontrase con la necesidad de subir un volcado SQL muy grande a un servidor y no tener acceso remoto al servidor mysql y, tampoco, tener acceso via shell, es decir la &amp;ldquo;única&amp;rdquo; vía es usar &lt;strong>PhpMyAdmin&lt;/strong>.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>He puesto ú_nica_  entre comillas por que desde luego hay muchas más alternativas, algunas muy manuales, o algunas más cómodas como la que os propongo: **&lt;a href="http://www.ozerov.de/bigdump/">Bigdump&lt;/a> **&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>¿Cuentas tuteladas para menores en las redes sociales?</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/05/24/cuentas-tuteladas-para-menores-en-las-redes-sociales/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/05/24/cuentas-tuteladas-para-menores-en-las-redes-sociales/</guid><description>&lt;p>Las redes sociales cada día están más presentes y ya forman parte de la vida de muchos de nosotros. Sin llegar a ser una dependencia,  son una herramienta que nos permite estar en contacto con nuestros amigos y conocidos, como antes lo fueron las postales, las cartas, y el teléfono fijo por ejemplo.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La edad mínima para acceder a una red social son los 14 años (al menos para &lt;strong>Facebook&lt;/strong> y &lt;strong>Tuenti&lt;/strong> en España), pero es sabido por todos que los menores intentan acceder a estas redes mucho antes, obligando a los administradores de las redes a &lt;a href="http://www.lne.es/sociedad-cultura/2010/06/24/tuenti-borrado-35000-perfiles-menores-14-anos-primer-semestre-2010/933494.html">eliminar muchas cuentas creadas por menores de 14 años&lt;/a>.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>¿Qué estabas haciendo hace un año? Las redes sociales te lo recuerdan</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/05/09/que-estabas-haciendo-hace-un-ano-las-redes-sociales-te-lo-recuerdan/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 May 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/05/09/que-estabas-haciendo-hace-un-ano-las-redes-sociales-te-lo-recuerdan/</guid><description>&lt;p>Las redes sociales que usamos habitualmente: &lt;strong>Facebook&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>Twitter&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>Foursquare&lt;/strong>, &lt;strong>instagram&lt;/strong>, etc. son, al fin y al cabo, una especie de diario de nosotros mismos, de lo que hacemos, de donde hemos estado, las fotos que hemos sacado, etc&amp;hellip; &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://timehop.com/">Timehop&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> es una herramienta, que una vez logueados en las distintas redes, nos enviará un email diariamente (o podemos acceder a su web para verlo) con un resumen de las entradas que hemos publicado en las redes sociales justo hace un año. Muy interesante para rememorar hecho pasados.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Como descargar un sitio web completo a tu equipo con wget</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/04/17/como-descargar-un-sitio-web-completo-tu-equipo-con-wget/</link><pubDate>Tue, 17 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/04/17/como-descargar-un-sitio-web-completo-tu-equipo-con-wget/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hace unos días me surgió la necesidad de descargar un sitio web completo a mi disco duro como copia y referencia. Conocía la existencia de algunas herramientas como Httrack, una aplicación multiplataforma (Windows, OSX, Linux) que nos permite descargar un sitio web completo al disco duro modificando incluso los enlaces para que sea perfectamente navegable sin conexión. Pero los usuarios de linux tenemos una alternativa más simple pero igual de potente wget wget es un comando que nos permite descargar cualquier contenido en la red a nuestro equipo, normalmente se emplea para descargar ficheros sueltos: html, imágenes, vídeos, etc&amp;hellip; pero con los parámetros adecuados puede descargar un sitio web completo&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Disconect.me: Navega de forma privada</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/04/10/disconectme-navega-de-forma-privada/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/04/10/disconectme-navega-de-forma-privada/</guid><description>&lt;p>Con la proliferación de los plugins &amp;lsquo;sociales&amp;rsquo;, que están cada día presentes en más paginas, la navegación privada comenzaba a ser una utopía. Por ejemplo, por el simple hecho de tener una sesión abierta (o no) en &lt;strong>Facebook&lt;/strong>, cada vez que entramos en una web que dispone de un inocente botón &amp;ldquo;Me gusta&amp;rdquo;, podremos ser identificados.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Esto no quiere decir que se haga, pero la posibilidad esta ahí.  La web que visitamos no sabe (o no tiene que saber quienes somos), pero el plugin social si que sabe quienes somos y que web estamos visitando, ya que tiene nuestra sesión en la red social y la página que pide mostrar el plugin.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cookies en un IFRAME en Internet Explorer: p3p policy</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/02/22/cookies-en-un-iframe-en-internet-explorer-p3p-policy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/02/22/cookies-en-un-iframe-en-internet-explorer-p3p-policy/</guid><description>&lt;p>Si desarrollas  una aplicación PHP web que trabaja dentro de un IFRAME  lo más probable es que necesite usar una sesión y para almacenar el id de la sesión necesitarás una &lt;strong>cookie&lt;/strong> (de esto se encarga el propio PHP) pero deberás tener en cuenta algunas consideraciones para evitarte &lt;strong>problemas de funcionamiento en Internet Explorer 6+&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>IE considera que el contenido del IFRAME es &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>contenido de terceras partes&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo; y siguiendo la configuración por defecto de seguridad del navegador  &lt;strong>bloqueará las cookies&lt;/strong> del IFRAME y por lo tanto perderás la sesión. Siempre existe la posibilidad de emplear el método de paso de sesión por URL, pero solo resolverá el problema respecto a PHP si usas otro tipo de herramientas que necesiten sesiones (Facebook, Twitter, etc) estas no tendrán acceso a su cookie.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>CCK Blocks: Separa los campos de un nodo</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/02/15/cck-blocks-separa-los-campos-de-un-nodo/</link><pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2012/02/15/cck-blocks-separa-los-campos-de-un-nodo/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hoy me gustaría presentarte, si aún no lo conoces, el módulo CCK Blocks. Un sencillo y útil módulo que nos permite mostrar los campos de un nodo en bloques, lo que nos da una mayor flexibilidad a la hora de maquetar y de mostrar la información. &lt;/p>
&lt;p>Esta disponible para descargar en &lt;a href="http://drupal.org/project/cck_blocks">http://drupal.org/project/cck_blocks&lt;/a>, una vez instalado, accedemos a la configuración el tipo de contenido que ya tengamos creado y editamos los campos que deseemos mostrar por separado. &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Backup incremental sobre FTP con rsync + curlftpfs</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/12/13/backup-incremental-sobre-ftp-con-rsync-curlftpfs/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/12/13/backup-incremental-sobre-ftp-con-rsync-curlftpfs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Seguro que en alguna ocasión has necesitado realizar un &lt;em>backup&lt;/em> de un sitio web al que solo tienes acceso mediante &lt;strong>ftp&lt;/strong>. Lo habitual es emplear un cliente ftp tipo &lt;a href="http://filezilla-project.org/">filezilla&lt;/a> o directamente trabajando en bash. El problema se plantea cuando, por ejemplo necesitamos realizar una copia incremental del sitio web y no tenemos acceso &lt;strong>ssh&lt;/strong> sobre el que pueda trabajar **&lt;a href="http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rsync">rsync&lt;/a> **o &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://www.cis.upenn.edu/~bcpierce/unison/">unison&lt;/a>&lt;/strong>. La solución nos la da &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://curlftpfs.sourceforge.net/">curlftpfs&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> que nos permite montar un directorio ftp en nuestro sistema para tratarlo como si fuese una carpeta local y realizar un rsyn o unison de forma normal.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Reuniones presenciales vs reuniones online</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/09/22/reuniones-presenciales-vs-reuniones-online/</link><pubDate>Thu, 22 Sep 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/09/22/reuniones-presenciales-vs-reuniones-online/</guid><description>&lt;p>En los últimos años se han puesto a nuestra disposición multitud de herramientas de trabajo para gestionar y realizar reuniones con clientes y colaboradores, y el crecimiento de la banda ancha y los dispositivos móviles con conexión a internet hace que todavía sea más sencillo realizar una reunión en la que sus integrantes se encuentran en sitios dispares.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Como cualquier cambio social y cultural, lo nuevo no elimina a lo antiguo, lo desplaza y le deja los reductos donde lo nuevo no es tan efectivo, hay multitud de ejemplos de esto:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Convertir tablas InnoDB en MyISAM</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/29/convertir-tablas-innodb-en-myisam/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/29/convertir-tablas-innodb-en-myisam/</guid><description>&lt;p>Recientemente me surgió la necesidad de convertir &lt;em>motor&lt;/em> de las tablas de una base de datos que usaban &lt;strong>InnoDB a MyISAM&lt;/strong>, la solución es trivial en apariencia, es decir, convertir una tabla es tan sencillo como&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>ALTER TABLE [NOMBRE_BBDD].[NOMBRE_TABLA] engine=MyISAM;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Pero si son muchas las tablas a convertir esta tarea se puede convertir en insufrible haciéndonos perder un valioso tiempo, e aquí la solución:&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>SELECT CONCAT(&amp;#39;ALTER TABLE &amp;#39;,table_schema,&amp;#39;.&amp;#39;,table_name,&amp;#39; engine=MyISAM;&amp;#39;) FROM information_schema.tables WHERE ENGINE = &amp;#39;InnoDB&amp;#39; AND table_schema = &amp;#39;[NOMBRE_BASE_DE_DATOS]&amp;#39;
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Con esta consulta conseguimos como resultado una cantidad de &lt;a href="http://es.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tupla">tuplas&lt;/a> igual al numero de tablas a convertir como único contenido de cada uno de ellos es la consulta SQL necesaria para convertir la tabla. Ya solo nos queda ejecutar las consultas obtenidas y &lt;em>voilá&lt;/em> tendremos nuestras tablas convetidas a &lt;em>MyISAM&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Moviendo tu blog wordpress de dominio</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/12/moviendo-tu-blog-wordpress-de-dominio/</link><pubDate>Fri, 12 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/12/moviendo-tu-blog-wordpress-de-dominio/</guid><description>&lt;p>En ocasiones necesitamos cambiar una página realizada en &lt;em>Wordpress&lt;/em> de ruta o de dominio, esto puede deberse simplemente a que estabamos trabajando en una copia local y una vez finalizada la llevamos al servidor definitivo, o por que queremos hacer funcionar nuestro blog, que tenemos en un servidor , en local.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Wordpress guarda en la base de datos información referenciada a rutas absolutas, por lo que una vez movido el blog dejará de funcionar o no lo hará de una forma correcta.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Nueva rama de desarrollo en Node.js y nueva imagen de marca</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/08/nueva-rama-de-desarrollo-en-nodejs-y-nueva-imagen-de-marca/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/08/nueva-rama-de-desarrollo-en-nodejs-y-nueva-imagen-de-marca/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>Node.js&lt;/strong> del que ya hemos hablado en posts anteriores, acaba de publicar una nueva rama (&lt;em>branch&lt;/em>) de desarrollo, la 0.5.x, sobre la que seguir creciendo. Hay numerosos cambios y &lt;em>bugfixes&lt;/em> que podeis conocer &lt;a href="https://github.com/joyent/node/wiki/ChangeLog">aqui&lt;/a>. La rama estable continua siendo la 0.4.x, Este es un momento importante para el proyecto que continua su desarrollo. Muestra de esto es al apoyo de Microsoft para crear un &lt;em>port&lt;/em> sobre la &lt;a href="http://blog.nodejs.org/2011/06/23/porting-node-to-windows-with-microsoft%e2%80%99s-help/">plataforma Windows&lt;/a> También ha aprovechado para evolucionar la marca y crear una &lt;a href="http://blog.nodejs.org/2011/07/11/evolving-the-node-js-brand/">nueva imagen corporativa&lt;/a> más consistente e identificable.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Ocultar código comentado en plantillas PHP</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/03/ocultar-codigo-comentado-en-plantillas-php/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/08/03/ocultar-codigo-comentado-en-plantillas-php/</guid><description>&lt;p>Un post fresquito para el verano ;) Cuando trabajamos con plantillas &lt;strong>php&lt;/strong>, como las que usan &lt;strong>Drupal&lt;/strong> o **Wordpress, **en las que introducimos nuestras variables directamente el &lt;em>html&lt;/em> mediante _php, _en ocasiones, sobre todo cuando estamos realizando pruebas o cambios solicitados por el cliente necesitamos comentar parte del código, tanto &lt;em>php&lt;/em> como _html, _para poder volver fácilmente a el si algo va mal.   Podemos caer en la tentación de usar las etiquetas de comentarios de html &lt;strong>&lt;/strong>, esto ocultará lo que no queremos ver, pero el php dentro del comentario continuará ejecutandose. De esta forma es más probable que aparezcan errores en el nuevo código además de perjudicar el tiempo de ejecución y carga de la página ya que estamos procesando y enviado al navegador elementos que no van a ser mostrados. La solución es tan sencilla como elegante, solo tenemos que introducir todo el código (html y php) a comentar dentro de comentarios de php Veamos un ejemplo:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Google Plus, ¿la nueva red social?</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/07/14/google-plus-la-nueva-red-social/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/07/14/google-plus-la-nueva-red-social/</guid><description>&lt;p>Ya han pasado unas semanas desde la presentación de &lt;a href="http://plus.google.com">Google+&lt;/a>, y ha superado todas las expectativas de la propia Google, se habla de 30 millones de usuarios antes de final de mes. Estas cifras son sorprendentes y analizadas sin tener en cuenta el contexto actual son muy sorprendentes y favorables, pero comparativamente con el gigante de las redes sociales &lt;strong>Facebook&lt;/strong> son irrisorias. Actualmente Facebook cuenta con 550 millones de usuarios en todo el mundo y aunque empieza a mostrar estancamiento, o incluso perdida de usuarios, en algunos paises  (USA y UK, por ejemplo) aún tiene potencial para seguir creciendo.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Chat en tu navegador con node.js y Faye</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/07/12/chat-en-tu-navegador-con-nodejs-y-faye/</link><pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/07/12/chat-en-tu-navegador-con-nodejs-y-faye/</guid><description>&lt;p>Siguiendo con los posts sobre &lt;strong>faye&lt;/strong>, vamos a realizar un ejemplo práctico y muy vistoso, vamos a realizar un sencillo pero funcional  &lt;strong>chat&lt;/strong> web en este post.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lo primero es crear el servidor node: Solo tenemos que incluir la extensión de &lt;strong>faye&lt;/strong> para &lt;strong>node&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code> var Faye = require(&amp;#39;./faye/faye-node.js&amp;#39;); var fayeServer = new Faye.NodeAdapter({&amp;amp;nbsp; mount: &amp;amp;nbsp; &amp;amp;nbsp;&amp;#39;/&amp;#39;}); fayeServer.listen(8888);
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>A este fichero lo llamaremos &lt;em>node.js&lt;/em>, ahora desde &lt;em>bash&lt;/em> lanzamos el servidor que acabamos de crear: &lt;code>$ node node.js&lt;/code>
Y ya tenemos nuestro &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>servidor de chat&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em> corriendo, preparado para funcionar En el lado cliente creamos un sencillo html y un script para gestionar el chat:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mejorando node.js: Faye</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/07/11/mejorando-nodejs-faye/</link><pubDate>Mon, 11 Jul 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/07/11/mejorando-nodejs-faye/</guid><description>&lt;p>Como ya comentamos en una entrada anterior &lt;strong>node.js&lt;/strong> es una herramienta muy potente, que nos permite crear servidores empleando javascript como lenguaje de programación en el servidor, pero puede ser costoso crear ciertas herramientas y protocolos desde 0. &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://faye.jcoglan.com/node.html" title="Faye">Faye&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> es una capa (extensión) sobre &lt;strong>node.js&lt;/strong>, lógicamente escrita en javascript, que crea un sistema de publicación y suscripción a canales de mensajes basados en el protocolo &lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://svn.cometd.com/trunk/bayeux/bayeux.html">Bayeux&lt;/a>.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En otras palabras, &lt;strong>faye&lt;/strong> se encarga de gestionar los canales, los envios de mensajes y la recepción por parte de los subscriptores a esos canales. &lt;strong>Faye&lt;/strong> consta de dos partes, una en el lado servidor y otra en el lado cliente (también escrita en javascript) Para explicar el funcionamiento de &lt;strong>faye&lt;/strong> más fácilmente pongamos un ejemplo: Imaginemos que estamos creando una aplicación que necesita enviar notificaciones en tiempo real a todos los usuarios conectados a una página. En nuestro &lt;em>script&lt;/em> para &lt;strong>node.js&lt;/strong> instroducimos lo siguiente:&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>3D sin plugins en tu navegador con javascript: three.js</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/06/27/3d-sin-plugins-en-tu-navegador-con-javascript-threejs/</link><pubDate>Mon, 27 Jun 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/06/27/3d-sin-plugins-en-tu-navegador-con-javascript-threejs/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hasta hace muy poco necesitábamos plugins, para realizar tareas que ahora nos parecen triviales, reproducir sonido, ver videos, hasta la más simple de las animación de un botón. Pero esto esta cambiando, la evolución de los navegadores es frenética y la próxima liberación de la especificación final de &lt;strong>HTML5&lt;/strong> y &lt;strong>CSS3&lt;/strong> y otros estandares (actualmente son borradores), nos hace pensar que podremos tener pronto una nueva revolución en la web. Permitiendo a los creativos dar rienda suelta a sui imaginación sin chocar con la usabilidad, la accesibilidad y el posicionamiento como sucede hasta la fecha.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Websites para móviles</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/04/29/websites-para-moviles/</link><pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/04/29/websites-para-moviles/</guid><description>&lt;p>Existe un gran debate acerca de que soluciones usar cuando adaptemos un website a móviles. Por lo normal, usar CSS (style sheets) como solución, nos ayuda a crear distintas visualizaciones sobre diferentes dispositivos móviles, pero no todos los fabricantes siguen los &lt;a href="http://www.w3.org/TR/css-mobile/">estándares&lt;/a>. El resultado sobre algunos en ellos puede ser impredecible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Hay diversidad de tipos de móviles. En algunos solo se puede visualizar los elementos gráficos más esenciales, como las webs de principios de la década. En otros, como los smartphones, pueden mostrar mejor el contenido web e incluso tener más funciones, ejecutar jQuery Mobile, etc. Aunque alguno de ellos, por ejemplo iPhone, no funciona, ni funcionará tecnología Flash. Para sacar el máximo partido a un website, proponemos dos opciones:  &lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Spam Social</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/04/07/spam-social/</link><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2011/04/07/spam-social/</guid><description>&lt;p>El spam es una de las actividades más molesta de internet, nos hace consumir nuestro tiempo en filtrar la información que recibimos.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Desgraciadamente estamos ya acostumbrados a la forma original de spam, la que nos llega por correo electrónico, pero poco a poco los filtros antispam han mejorado mucho y es posible reducir la cantidad de spam recibida.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Con el nacimiento y posterior expansión de las redes sociales los spammers han modificado la forma en la que nos hacian llegar spam para acosarnos en Facebook, Twitter, MySpace, etc&amp;hellip; Pero la novedad de esta spam es que &lt;strong>¡nos lo envian nuestros amigos!&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Música invisible</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/11/26/musica-invisible/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Nov 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/11/26/musica-invisible/</guid><description>&lt;p>Soy un gran consumidor de música a través de servicios de streaming como &lt;a href="http://www.spotify.com">spotify&lt;/a>, &lt;a href="http://www.lastfm.com">last.fm&lt;/a> y otros. Creo que es el futuro de la música, ese futuro que avanza como una tsunami y al que algunos tratan de poner freno por los médios que sea.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>La música estan en su mejor momento (&lt;strong>música≠discográficas&lt;/strong>), pero los hábitos de consumo estan cambiando, por lo menos en lo que a mi atañe. Ya no quiero tener la música almacenada en CDs por que es un formato incómo, si quiero escuchar un tema en concreto tengo que buscar el CD donde esta, y metelo en el ordenador.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Node.js: Javascript power!!</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/10/25/nodejs-javascript-power2/</link><pubDate>Mon, 25 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/10/25/nodejs-javascript-power2/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;strong>&lt;a href="http://www.nodejs.org">Node.js&lt;/a>&lt;/strong> es un entorno de programación de entrada/salida orientada a eventos, sobre el motor de Javascript &lt;strong>V8&lt;/strong> (el mismo que usa Google Chrome)&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;em>Pero ¿Que quiere decir todo esto? ¿Y para que me puede servir?&lt;/em>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Lo más básico que podemos realizar con &lt;strong>node.js&lt;/strong> es un servidor web (HTTP).&lt;/p>
&lt;pre tabindex="0">&lt;code>var http = require(&amp;#39;http&amp;#39;);

http.createServer(function (req, res) {

 res.writeHead(200, {&amp;#39;Content-Type&amp;#39;: &amp;#39;text/plain&amp;#39;});

 res.end(&amp;#39;Hello World\n&amp;#39;);

}).listen(8124, &amp;#34;127.0.0.1&amp;#34;);
&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;p>Con estas pocas lineas tenemos un servidor web escuchando el puerto 8124 funcionando en nuestro equipo y respondiendonos siempre &amp;ldquo;&lt;em>Hello World&lt;/em>&amp;rdquo;&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Servidor de Máquinas virtuales remotas con Virtualbox</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/10/19/servidor-de-maquinas-virtuales-remotas-con-virtualbox/</link><pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/10/19/servidor-de-maquinas-virtuales-remotas-con-virtualbox/</guid><description>&lt;p>Para un desarrollador de web, es muy importante tener un entorno de desarrollo y de prueba completamente optimizado.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>En el apartado de pruebas lo recomendable es que probemos nuestros desarrollos web con la mayor cantidad de navegadores posibles.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Si como es nuestro caso, empleas Linux como sistema operativo de desarrollo, podras probar si problema la mayoria de los navegadores: Firefox, Chrome, Opera, Konqueror, etc, (incluso Safari usando &lt;strong>wine)&lt;/strong>, pero hay un navegador que se nos va a escapar y que por desgracia para la web es ampliamente utilizado: &lt;strong>Internet Explorer.&lt;/strong>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Usabilidad: Notificaciones en el título de la página</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/08/25/usabilidad-notificaciones-en-el-titulo-de-la-pagina/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2010 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2010/08/25/usabilidad-notificaciones-en-el-titulo-de-la-pagina/</guid><description>&lt;p>Hoy en dia la mayoria de los usuarios cuando estamos navegando tenemos abiertas simultaneamente varias pestañas en el navegador. A veces nuestra aplicación web necesita llamar la atención del usuario para requerir de el una acción o simplemente hacerle sabes que ha recibido una notificación.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Una buena manera de hacerlo es cambiar alternativamente el título de la página por un aviso, de la misma forma que hace facebook cuando recibimos una notificación de chat; el título de la página cambia 3 o 4 veces entre &amp;ldquo;Facebook&amp;hellip;.&amp;rdquo; y &amp;ldquo;Fulanito te ha enviado un mensaje&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>About me</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/about/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/about/</guid><description>&lt;p>I discovered computers when I was child in a moment the home computers started to be more common. My first computer was
an &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Amstrad_CPC">Amstrad CPC 464&lt;/a> with a green-screen, in that moment I understood and
wanted to learn more about computers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>As child I started to program in BASIC, then QBASIC and later Turbo Pascal (I keep an example rescued from an old floppy
disk: &lt;a href="https://bitbucket.org/sergiocarracedo/liga-fantastica-marca/src/master/">https://bitbucket.org/sergiocarracedo/liga-fantastica-marca/src/master/&lt;/a>)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Blog posts by year</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/by-year/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/blog/by-year/</guid><description/></item><item><title>Cookies</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/cookies/</link><pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/cookies/</guid><description>&lt;p>Esta web, como otras muchas, utiliza cookies que permitirán mejorar su experiencia como usuario y en cumplimiento de la
LSSI (LEY 34/2002, de 11 de julio, de servicios de la sociedad de la información y de comercio electrónico), vamos a
informarle sobre que son, cuales utilizamos en nuestra web, como eliminarlas y le pediremos el consentimiento para su
uso.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="información">INFORMACIÓN&lt;/h2>
&lt;h3 id="qué-son-las-cookies">¿Qué son las cookies?&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>Son pequeños archivos de texto que se descargan e instalan en su ordenador o en su móvil a través de su navegador (
Internet Explorer, Firefox, Chrome, Safari…) o a través de una aplicación Flash. Las cookies permiten que las webs le
“recuerden”, ya sea durante una visita (mediante las llamadas “cookies de sesión”) o durante varias visitas (mediante
las llamadas “cookies persistentes”) y almacenen información sobre sus preferencias para ofrecerle una experiencia
personalizada, más fácil y más rápida. Solamente el servidor que la instaló podrá leer su contenido, que por otra parte,
será anónimo. Aunque se instalen en su disco duro, al ser solo texto, no son capaces por sí mismas de acceder a
información personal de su ordenador, ni a trasmitir virus, tan solo rastrean la navegación sobre un sitio web. A
continuación le explicamos cuales son las cookies según su función:&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>