<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Hardware on Sergio Carracedo</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/tags/hardware/</link><description>Recent content in Hardware on Sergio Carracedo</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/tags/hardware/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Monsgeek M5 custom keyboard review</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/monsgeek-m5-custom-keybord-review/</link><pubDate>Sun, 23 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/monsgeek-m5-custom-keybord-review/</guid><description>&lt;p>5 years ago I bought my &lt;a href="https://sergiocarracedo.es/2019/05/25/Impresiones-tras-un-mes-de-uso-de-un-teclado-mecanico/">first mechanical keyboard&lt;/a>, a cheap and simply one, the Krom Kernel, a 100% size keyboard with Outemu Red switches with spanish layout. During this time I change the space bar keycap twice because the plastic was not very good and the part that connects with the switch was not very reliable and it broke causing a bad experience pressing it. But was something I could fix, replacing all the keycaps with a better quality ones.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A real-world "on a meeting" light sign</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/a-real-world-on-a-meeting-light-sign/</link><pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/a-real-world-on-a-meeting-light-sign/</guid><description>&lt;p>Me and my wife work remotely and we do it in the same room, but there is a problem: the meetings, and
obviously, working remotely we have, let&amp;rsquo;s say, more than we would like, and is not always easy to know when the other
is in a meeting.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I decided to find a solution to make it visible when someone is in a meeting simply, only with a sight.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The solution: Put a light sign on the working room&amp;rsquo;s wall and turn it on when I am in a meet and off when I am not,
simple. :)&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>elgato Stream Deck on Linux</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/stream-deck-linux/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/stream-deck-linux/</guid><description>&lt;p>Last Christmas I got a &lt;a href="https://www.elgato.com/en/gaming/stream-deck">Elgato Stream Deck&lt;/a> as a present. My very beginning thoughts were: &amp;ldquo;I don&amp;rsquo;t need this, I don&amp;rsquo;t know a real use case for that&amp;rdquo;. But I decided to keep it and try to use it for something.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="what-is-a-_stream-deck_">What is a &lt;em>Stream Deck&lt;/em>?&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>The &lt;em>Stream Deck&lt;/em> is a device with 15 buttons (in my case), each button has a small screen that can show an icon or a text. The device is connected to your computer via USB and it has software that allows you to configure each button and the action to do when you press it. I think it&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;stream&amp;rdquo; because one of the typical use cases is to change the &lt;a href="https://obsproject.com/">OBS&lt;/a> scenes when you are streaming, but in general terms, you can control anything you want. You can think on it as a macro keyboard with customizable buttons, both action and key visualization.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Slimbook ProX 15: First Impressions</title><link>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/04/05/slimbook-prox15-first-impressions/</link><pubDate>Sun, 05 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://sergiocarracedo.es/2020/04/05/slimbook-prox15-first-impressions/</guid><description>&lt;p>As you probably know, I started a new job this year, and my company provided me a laptop. They asked me which laptop I would like to use to work, most people would answer: MacBook Pro or something like that, but I don&amp;rsquo;t like Apple (sorry, those are my likes, maybe you have different ones), and I prefer Linux as my OS.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>My first choice was a Dell XPS 15 with 16GB of RAM, but after several delays in delivery, my company and I were tired of waiting and we decided to order another laptop.&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>