<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>data visualization on Sergio Carracedo</title><link>/tags/data-visualization/</link><description>Recent content in data visualization on Sergio Carracedo</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en-us</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/tags/data-visualization/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Using charts in the frontend: Echarts with examples</title><link>/using-charts-frontend-echarts-with-examples/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>/using-charts-frontend-echarts-with-examples/</guid><description>If you are working in frontend and in data visualization one of the tasks you need to solve is to represent data in different ways (charts) and there are multiple ways of resolving it:
Do it from the scratch, with js and css, svg, canvas, etc Using a low-level library that abstracts for you things like dom manipulation, scales, etc, d3.js is a very good one: I wrote a blog post about it Using chart libraries Let&amp;rsquo;s see some pros and cons of the different approaches there is no perfect solution, depends on your needs.</description></item><item><title>Creating a simple donut progress chart</title><link>/2020/05/18/Creating-a-simple-donut-chart/</link><pubDate>Mon, 18 May 2020 09:28:03 +0000</pubDate><guid>/2020/05/18/Creating-a-simple-donut-chart/</guid><description>One of more simpler charts you can create is a circular chart to represent the percent of completion of something.
First approximation We could create a SVG document to draw our donut. SVG allow us to represent graphical elements, for example, cicles, rectangles, polygons, etc&amp;hellip; using XML (and therefore accesing to the elements via DOM). SVG is vertorial and is perfect for responsive.
Figure 1 represent that kind of chart, if the value is 100% the donut is perfect, if is 50% donut is a half donut, and 0% means no donut.</description></item></channel></rss>